本字幕由 YYeTs人人影视 原创翻译制作
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
更多影视更新 请登陆 www.YYeTs.net
■
翻译：蛋生  X-Ray  Tiberius zoor  校对：Joanna
时间轴：崽猪  后期&特效：csbeyond
顾问：小跳  Tiberius  总监：Joanna  鱼骨头
■
战场上最致命的武器  狙击手
He's the deadliest weapon on the battlefield-- the sniper.
一旦目标锁定  绝无闪失
Once you've hunted man, nothing else matters.
无处可藏
There is nowhere to hide.
如果我们经过观察
If we are looking at you,
判定你是危险份子
and you have deemed yourself a bad guy,
那么你必死无疑
we're going to be there to kill you.
从越南战争到史上最远射程的狙击
From Vietnam to the longest kill shot in history.
他们以为自己能侥幸生还  可惜想错了
They thought that day was their lucky day, but it wasn't.
狙击手带来世上的终极射击
The world's most extreme shots
狙击手的信条是
executed by men who live the sniper's creed:
一枪毙命
"One shot One kill."
狙击手
身
在
瞄  准  镜
本片揭示了史上最危险的狙击任务
其中包括一些残酷的战争场面
部分场景已作特殊处理  请酌情观看
狙击手在战场上的任务异常艰巨
Being a sniper in combat is a very radical situation.
你要清楚自己在做什么
You got to understand what you're doing.
你的目标是活人
You're hunting other human beings.
模拟场景
彻查周围  射杀目标
When you're looking through that scope and you take a target out,
效果立竿见影
the immediate effect it has on those around them--
对方的整个行动被迫中止
their whole agenda is now stopped.
现在换我行动  都是我囊中之物
Now it's my agenda. I own them.
梦幻之击
射杀背景:伊拉克  拉马迪  2005年
The hunting ground: Ramadi.Iraq.2005.
伊拉克  拉马迪  2005年
开始进驻拉马迪时
When we first rolled into Ramadi,
一周约有95到100起路边爆炸事件
the IED rate was approximately 95 to a hundred IEDs a week.
我们的任务就是
Our-our mission was to just
模拟场景
找到埋放路边炸弹的份子  将其剔除
find people emplacing IEDs and to take them out.
伊拉克
驻伊美军有这样一则信条
GIs fighting in Iraq have a motto:
拉马迪
纬度:33.427588  经度:43.298837
礼貌  专业  杀人需谋定而后动
Be polite, be professional and have a plan to kill everyone you meet
如果我们经过观察
If we are looking at you,
判定你是危险份子
and you have deemed yourself a bad guy,
那么你必死无疑
we're going to be there to kill you.
狙击手  詹姆斯・格里兰军士长
The sniper, first Sergeant James Gilliland.
保持着7.62口径狙击步枪最远射杀记录:
Longest kill shot with a 7.62 caliber rifle:
0.7英里[约为1250米]
Seven-tenths of a mile.
一旦此人有所行动  造成威胁
Once the individual takes that step and crosses the line,
就会成为我们的目标
then he comes into our world.
成为狙击目标
He comes as a target.
格里兰与影子队
Gilliland and Shadow Team,
十人狙击小组
a ten-man Army sniper unit,
埋伏在城市的各个角落  观察敌方行动
watch insurgent activity from hides throughout the city.
六个月内共射杀276人
They rank up 276 kills in six months.
查清预定目标行动路线的
One of the biggest techniques that we use to
其中一项最关键技术
find where our next targets were going to be
与猎鹿和火鸡很相似
is directly related to deer hunting or turkey hunting.
要观察整个地区
We'd observe an area,
就像猎手在狩猎季节前做的
just like a lot of hunters do in pre-season,
把所见都印在脑子里
take mental pictures of what you're seeing,
记住哪里有利于狙击  哪里是盲区
what you can and can't see from what angles.
这些都要记忆  就像一位猎手
You start learning the players just like a hunter would learn,
要记住自己狩猎区的动物一样
you know, what animals are in his hunting area.
安德鲁・贝亚特
影子队狙击手
观察每一处
You watch everything
并印在脑子里
and you just kind of remember it in your head.
我们对城中每个人都了如指掌
We knew pretty much everyone in the town
因某些原因  其中很多人都蒙着脸
and for some reason, a lot of them would wear masks,
这更容易暴露
which was a big giveaway.
目标指示器
我不明白他们为什么要这么做
I don't know why they would even do that.
没错  伊拉克戴着滑雪面罩的家伙
Yeah, you see a guy in a ski mask in Iraq,
都是来者不善
that's a bad guy.
影子队主要的藏身之处
Shadow Team sets up its main hide
藏身地点
设在H号观察哨
on the rooftop of the O.P.Hotel,
俯瞰整个密西根路
overlooking Route Michigan,
H号观察哨
密西根路
这是拉马迪的主要街道
the major roadway through Ramadi.
它曾是整个城市最高的建筑
It was the tallest building in the city,
显然  我们可以进行全方位监视
so obviously, we had 360-degree observation.
我们将这个顶楼藏身地称为"乌鸦窝"
We're pretty much on the roof in the, what we called crow's nest.
格里兰向他的队员强调两点
Gilliland preaches two things to his team:
多重火力  射击躯干
multiple weapon engagements and body shots.
又名  质心瞄准
AKA center mass holds.
质心就是胸甲护着的地方
Basically, center mass is just under the breastplate.
不仅射击面比较宽
It would not only give you a larger target surface to hit,
质心瞄准
对狙击手心理影响也会降低
but also it could be used as, uh, desensitizing,
让你感觉不是在瞄准一个人
um, in a way that you're not looking at the individual.
不突出面部特征
Instead of picking out a facial feature to engage,
像是瞄准一颗扣子
you are picking out a shirt button.
人们会认为  狙击时
In the sniper game, everybody wants to think
一定要瞄准头部
that the head shot is the way to go.
质心瞄准
我要纠正一下
I wanted to get away from that,
尤其是当时那种环境
especially in that environment.
通常会出现几个目标
Uh, there were multiple targets regularly,
与其耗时打中两人头部
and if you wasted the time to take two well-aimed head shots,
不如打中五人身体躯干
you could've taken five body shots and then
然后争取时间再瞄准或射杀敌人
come back and either captured or reengaged and killed the enemy.
一天的狙击任务大概是三至四人
We were probably engaging up to three or four targets a day,
有时更多
sometimes more.
我们把他们逼得越来越远
We moved them back further and further into a point
他们不在距离我们800米范围之内行动
where they wouldn't do anything within 800 meters of us
怕被我们干掉
because they were scared of us.
我们听到他们无数次在喊Knas
We heard many times--Knas
就是指"狙击手"
was Iraqi for "Sniper."
通过监听清真寺和其他地方的对讲机
And we'd hear over the intercoms of the mosques and stuff.
狙击手  狙击手  不断提到这个词
Bla bla bla...Knas, Knas, Knas, constantly.
他们总在相互提醒要小心我们
I think they were always warning people
我们就在附近  道理很简单
that we were out there, watched out us, because,
他们对我们心存恐惧
honestly, fears is the big factor.
六个月后
Over six months,
影子队铲除了附近埋放路边炸弹的人
Shadow Team clears their sector of IEDs,
但真正的危险却在楼顶
but the real danger will come from the rooftops.
2005年9月27日
我们当时要掩护一支队伍
We were overwatching one of the line companies.
这队人负责管制
They were doing a cordoned search in the
位于H号观察哨北部的工业区
industrial areas to the north side of the O.P. Hotel
为了获得最佳监视角度
A common practice for a lot of units
最常用的方法就是
to get the best observation they can get,
在建筑物的楼顶进行巡视
they would go to the rooftops of buildings.
一旦采用这种方法  就将暴露无疑
And when you do that, you skyline yourself.
就像长在山上的一棵孤树
just like you can see a single tree on the mountain,
直挺挺  异常显眼
if it sticks up above the mountain.
这些人当时就是如此
And that's essentially what these guys were doing.
完全把自己变成枪靶子
They were making targets of themselves.
我拨过去提醒他们
I called and I was like,
告诉杰森  让他蹲下
"Hey, you need to tell Jason he needs to get down"
提醒之后  也就一会儿工夫
And you know, lo and behold, a few minutes would go by and
他和其他几个人又站起来
he'd be standing up again with a couple of the other guys.
我又打过去  对他们说
I called back down there and was like,
告诉杰森  让他蹲下
"Hey, you know, you need to tell Jason he needs to get back down.
所有人都能看到他  我能看得清清楚楚
Everybody can see him. If I can see him where I'm at,
其他人也可以
everybody else can see him."
第三次看到他还站在楼顶时
When I saw this going on for the third time,
我又抓起对讲机
I picked the radio up.
正当我准备再次警告他
Right as I was going to go to key it to tell him,
再次提醒  让你的人都蹲下
Hey, you need to get those guys down, one more time.
送话钮还没来得及按下
Right before I pushed the the talk button is
只见他抽动了一下  倒在了地上
when I saw him jerk and he fell.
有人中枪  有人中枪
Man down! Man down!
有人从医院方向伏击我们
We're being shot at from the hospital!
我们负责掩护任务
We were providing overwatch
听到对讲机那头喊着
and then you hear over the radio,
有人中枪  敌方狙击手打中一人
"Man down. Someone just got shot by an enemy sniper."
于是  我们观察周围情况
So we are just glued to the scopes,
仔细检查每一处  想找出狙击手
looking everywhere, trying to find this sniper.
从医院方向查起
So, we start looking at the hospital and
格里兰军士长
Sergeant Gilliland saw
在顶层的一扇窗户外发现那人
the sniper in the window on one of the top floors.
我注意到那是四层
I noticed on the fourth floor,
有一人站在阳台上
there was a single individual standing in a bay window,
能清楚看到有人拿着
I could clearly make out
长枪管卡的拉什尼科夫式步枪
a loner barrel with Kalashnikov targer rifle
目标
从我们这里到医院距离是1250米
We knew that from our building to that hospital was 1250 meters
换算成英里是0.7英里
or seven-tenth a mile from our observation post.
那次任务我们使用的是M24式狙击步枪
The rifle we had for that was a standard shot: 24 sniper rifle.
武器型号: M24式狙击步枪
口径: 7.62X51mm
枪口初速: 每秒2600英尺
最大有效射程: 875码[约800米]
当时距离那个狙击手为1367码
via that sniper was 1367 yards away.
相当于13.5个橄榄球场
This distance is 13 and a half football fields.
超出他的M24式最大有效射程500码
nearly 500 yards beyond the max effective range of Glilliland's M24.
这种情况下  最佳结果不是打中目标
The perfect contain was not to make a one-round clean shot.
而是阻吓目标
It was to, at that distance, surprise target.
M24配有刘波尔德M3A型密位镜
M24 has a Leupold, M3A scope of fixed-power with a mil-dot
俯仰角调整手轮
and bullet drop compensator.
每个刻度代表一百码
You correlate the number to the amount of 100 yard to on the shoot
我把旋钮转到十  来打一千码
I turned that turn to ten to shoot for 1000 yards
快速预估了弹头下降幅度
A quick calculation, I estimated the bullet drop, decided that
我需要向上提高三个密位
I needed to hold about three miles over the target
来补偿弹道下降
to compensate for the drop.
在1367码距上  一个密位是4英尺
At 1,367 yards, each mil-dot represents four feet.
弹头下降幅度
12尺
因重力和空气阻力  漫长的飞行距离中
The great distance and severe drop of the bullet,
弹头会大幅下降
due to gravity and drag,
故要将准心移到目标上方12尺处
means Gilliland must aim 12 feet above the target.
此外还要考虑风速
And also, in doing that, had to allow for the wind,
风力对弹头的作用及弹头自转产生的偏差
which will push the round, as well as spin drift.
当弹头旋转着穿行于大气中时
As the round is flying through the air and spinning,
旋转偏离
其自身旋转所产生的力
the force that is caused by the actual spin
会导致其偏转
will cause it to rotate up and
从而偏离原来的运动轨道  道理等同于陀螺
away from the center line of the bore, much like a top.
陀螺在旋转过程中
It would eventually start
会向旋转的方向偏移
moving in the direction of the the spin.
子弹在运动时也会产生同样的偏移
It's the same way for the actual bullet.
不过偏移度有规律可循
It's measured and it's pretty constant,
可通过公式计算出来
so you can use a formula to account for that.
格里兰将准心向左留出8英尺提前量
Gilliland aims or "Holds off" eight feet left
以抵消风速和旋转带来的偏移
of the target to compensate for a light wind and spin drift.
这种方法也称"肯塔基风偏"
This compensation is known as Kentucy Windage.
肯塔基风偏
准心不压在目标上
Uh, the crosshairs were completely off-target.
只要感觉对了
Once I was comfortable with where my sight was,
扣动扳机即可
I just squeezed the round off.
我注意到  目标人物抽搐了一下
I noticed the target grimace and then,
随即倒在地上  没再站起来
He fell back and didn't see him come back up again.
看到对方倒地后  我转头对着观察手说
After the guy went down, I turned around and looked at my spotter,
"看到了吗"  接到报告说
I said, "Did you see that?" The report came back.
有一名男子倒在四楼的阳台上
There was a single individual, male, on the fourth floor balcony
胸部正中  中一枪
with a single, um, gunshot wound to the center of the chest.
角度非常精准
And the angle was pretty, pretty severe.
子弹位于其身体内  并且完整
So...the bullet actually was in it, in one part,
且留在了对方的身体里
and stopped somewhere inside the individual's body.
这种狙击任务中包含各种因素
There's, there's so many factors to a shot like that.
像这么远射程  这一枪简直是无可挑剔
And over a distance like that, it had to fall just perfect.
万里挑一
It was a one-in-a-million shot.
格里兰使用M24狙击步枪
Gilliland's kill shot at seven-tenths of a mile
完成0.7英里的狙击任务
with his M24 sniper rifle,
刷新了7.62mm口径的狙击记录
rewrites the record books for 7.62-caliber rifles.
其实  我当时并没指望打中这个人
In all honesty, I wasn't trying to necessarily engage the individual
只想尽力打在他的身边
as much as I was trying to get around
迫使他离开阳台
close enough to him to get him out of the window.
当时一心想阻止他狙击我们的人
I wanted to stop him from engaging, you know, our guys.
不过  这算是他自食恶果吧
Um, but he got what he got.
越南  1969年  一名海陆狙击手
Vietnam, 1969. A Marine sniper
在100码的范围内面对着几百个敌军
faces hundreds of enemy soldiers less than 100 yards away.
我十字线压着对方脑门
I've got the reticle right on his forehead,
然后迅速地一个接一个  全部干掉
and then as fast as I can move from one to the next,
只听到  "砰  砰  砰"
it was just, pow, pow, pow!
16次开火  16个位置
At 16 different battles at 16 different positions,
不容任何差池
and you can't miss.
否则自己必死无疑
Or you're dead.
弗吉尼亚州匡提科  精密武器区
Precision Weapons Section, Quantico, Virginia.
海军陆战队狙击步枪在此生产
The life of the Marine sniper rifle begins here.
伊森・普雷斯
前海军陆战队狙击手
这是M40X式狙击步枪  可谓是所有
This is the M40X sniper rifle and this is basically the father to--
目前装备使用的M40A3狙击步枪之父
the M40A3 is the modern sniper rifles that we use today.
使用这种武器系统射击难度更大
Much more difficult to shoot with this weapon system and
也是恰克・马嵬尼等狙击手成为传奇的原因之一
that's one of the reasons those guys like Chuck Mawhinney such legends
他们只配发简陋的狩猎步枪
they were given just the basic hunting rifle and unbelievable,
给敌人带来难以置信的毁灭性打击
the devastation that they were able to inflict.
已瞄准目标
On target.
择机开火
Fire when ready.
送你上西天  伙计
Say good night, fella.
16次射击  16次击毙
模拟场景
从我摸到雷明顿700步枪的那一刻
From the time I touched that Remington 700,
就深深爱上了它并决定成为狙击手
I was in love with it and I wanted to be a sniper.
我要去猎杀那些妄图杀死我的敌人
I'm gonna hunt something that's gonna hunt me back.
我喜欢那种感觉
Oh, I love that.
狙击手  恰克・马嵬尼
The sniper, Chuck Mawhinney.
确认毙敌103人  可能击杀216人
海陆史上最高毙敌纪录保持者
Most confirmed kills in Marine Corps history.
马嵬尼大开杀戒之地:南越  亚利桑那属地
Mawhinney's hunting ground: the Arizona Territory, South Vietnam.
北越
南越
亚利桑那属地
北纬15.844073度  东经108.061658度
该绰号因此地激烈的西部风格枪战而得来
Nicknamed for its Wild West-style firefights.
环境极其复杂
Environment is target-rich.
那地方真的很热
That was a really hot area.
各种复杂因素包罗其中
I mean, there was a lot of things going on.
极易于隐藏  也利于渗透
It was easy to hide, it was easy to move through,
对狙击手来说  这里得天独厚
as far as a sniper, you couldn't have found a better area.
马嵬尼的主战武器  M40狙击步枪
Mawhinney's primary weapon: the M40 sniper rifle,
有效杀伤距离1094码  相当于11个橄榄球场
deadly up to 1,094 yards-- the distance of 11 football fields.
M40狙击步枪
在那里以这个距离射击敌人时
You hit somebody out there at that distance,
他们无法确定来袭火力的方向
they're not sure where anything's coming from.
他一头栽倒之后
He got towards the end,
在那个距离上我们就看不到几个
we didn't see a lot of people stand around up in the open any more
站着暴露的敌人了
at these long distances
1969年  情人节
Valentine's Day, 1969.
马嵬尼与数百名
Mawhinney is on a collision course
狭路相逢
with hundreds of North Vietnamese soldiers.
天就要下雨了
And there was a monsoon coming in.
我们接到空中侦察报告说
We had a large NVA force reported by aircraft
大批北越军队正向我们的位置运动
moving towards our position and they said,
北越军队
马嵬尼
他们说由于下雨不能向我提供空中支援
"I can't get air support for you because of the monsoon.
我和我们的指挥官进行了沟通  我说
I talked with our CO about what was going on and I said,
我愿带上配星光瞄具的M14步枪和我的搭档
"I would like to take the M14, the Starlight, my partner and go down
晚上去那条河边进行警戒
and watch that river this evening
看他们是否企图渡河
and see if they try to cross it."
我们收拾行装启程前去
We loaded up our gear and headed down.
多数狙击手的攻击对象是300到1000码内的
Most sniper engagements are single targets
单个目标
at 300 to 1,000 yards.
而马嵬尼将面对的可能是
Mawhinney faces the possibility
距他不足100码的多个目标
of multiple targets within 100 yards of his position.
远射程能保证我们的安全
Our range is our safety,
克瑞斯特・杰克  美国海军陆战队
《一枪毙命》作者之一
能保持我们与目标的安全距离
our stand off.
如果我在1000码距离向你开枪
If I can shoot you at 1,000 yards,
在这个距离你甚至都看不到我
you can't even see me at 1,000 yards.
但你若离我二三十码的话
But if you are at 20 30 yards away from me,
你能看到能听到甚至嗅到我
you can see me, you can hear and you can smell me,
敌人很容易觉察到你
the enemy can taste you
马嵬尼未选用最擅长的手动上膛M40栓动步枪
Mawhinney swaps his trusty bolt action M40
而选用了他的副武器  M14半自动步枪
for his secondary weapon: a semiautomatic M14.
我很清楚我得尽量速战速决
I knew that I had to do it as fast as I could.
拖得越久就会给他们更多的时间
The longer time I took was more time for them
来作出反应  探明我们的位置
to start figuring out where we were, what was going on.
M14步枪使用弹匣供弹
The M14, you put a magazine in,
武器型号：M14半自动步枪
口径：7.62X51mm
枪口初速:每秒2800英尺
射速:750发每分
它是一种半自动武器
it's a semiautomatic weapon.
可以自动装填弹药
So, it automatically feeds.
将新一发子弹装入枪膛
That's less time for getting
预备击发所用的时间更短
a new round in the chamber ready to fire.
夜幕降临
Night falls.
马嵬尼和他的观察手隐蔽在
Mawhinney and his spotter conceal themselves
他们的最终射击位置  亦称FFP
at their final firing position or "FFP."
他们埋伏在能俯瞰河道最浅处的地方
Their hide overlooks the shallowest part of the river--
这里最有可能成为渡口
the most likely crossing point.
你在设置埋伏的时候
When you're setting up a hide,
就是在选择一个最方便你工作的地方
you're obviously picking a place where you're gonna work from.
我下埋伏时  我要求对目标区域有良好视野
What I wanna do is, I want a good view of where I want to shoot at,
并且具备理想的撤退路线
and I want a good escape and evasion route.
最终射击位置
河道自3点钟到9点钟方位经过
The river runs from 9:00 to 3:00,
在马嵬尼和敌人间形成了一道天然屏障
providing a natural barrier between Mawhinney and the enemy.
一片小泥滩位于12点钟方位
A small mudbank at 12:00
对轻武器射击起到保护
offers protection from small arms fire,
但提供了开阔的视野
but allows a clear field of view.
3点到9点方向分布的树林和灌木能提供隐蔽
Brush and foliage from 3:00 to 9:00 provide concealment.
马嵬尼的观察手负责保证该区域的安全
Mawhinney's spotter is responsible for security in this sector.
如果任务失败
If the mission is compromised,
他们的撤退路线位于5点钟方位
the Marines' escape route is at 5:00.
马嵬尼的瞄具  AN/PVS-2星光瞄准镜
Mawhinney's eye: An AN/PVS-2 Starlight Scope.
一种由周围光线触发的被动夜视系统
A passive night vision system activated by ambient light.
在星光瞄准镜里满眼都是绿色
Everything's in a real green tint through the Starlight
浅色的物体会更亮
and light things will show up brighter than others.
比如脸  皮肤和手
Like a face and skin and hands,
这些在瞄准镜下更为显眼
it really lights up through the scope.
星光瞄准镜需要
You gotta have some kind of
外界提供光源才能工作
external light for the Starlight to work.
如果是一片漆黑  那你什么也看不见
If it's just pitch, pitch black, you can't see anything.
马嵬尼来回观察着河对岸的动静
Mawhinney scans the river for any sign of the enemy.
那晚我们埋伏了好长时间
So we sit through that night for a long time
大约半小时后发现河对岸有动静
and about a half hour later we got movement on the other side.
有人下河准备渡河
Somebody gets in the river and they start coming across,
并正朝着我们走来
walking right straight at us.
步枪上膛  只待击发
Rifle's loaded, it's ready to go.
他离我足够近
He's close enough to me
我甚至能听到水从他身上滴下的声音
and I hear water dripping off of him.
我绝不能让他溜走通过草地
There's no way I can let him get between me and the company
并威胁到连队  那样我们就麻烦大了
and that elephant grass 'cause we're gonna have a mess.
我打开保险  扣向扳机
I've got the safety off and I'm putting pressure on the trigger.
我将准星对准他脸正中间
I've got the reticle right in the middle of his face
已经准备好送他上归西了
and I'm just getting ready to dispatch him.
可很快他又退回到河里
And then pretty soon he retreats back in the river
向河对岸退去
and goes back on to the other side.
我告诉我的搭档他极有可能因此被捕
I told my partner this might really get him arrested
马嵬尼等待着北越军的出现
Mawhinney waits for the NVA to appear.
脑海里构想着他的交火地域
He mentally visualizes his field of fire.
射杀区域的大概有一个橄榄球场的长度
The Kill Zone is roughly the length of one football field.
射杀区域
你要尽量不能让战火烧到你脚下
You try to basically play the game before it comes to you.
你要预测可能发生的情况并运用策略
You're anticipating what can happen and you're doing your strategy
比如  他们前进到这里该我怎么办
you know-- "What am I gonna do if they go here?
在这里我怎么对付他们
How can I funnel them here?
我怎么才能把他们引入最佳射击位置
What do I need to do to put them in the best position,
在什么位置我可以消灭目标
where I can eliminate the targets
我预先设想好了一切可能发生的情况
I got every picture in my mind, what was gonna take place.
所以当目标真正出现时  你对此已早有准备
So, when the actual targets actually show up, it's not something new.
此时你就不用考虑那一切了
Now you don't have to think about all that.
那已成为肌肉记忆  早已刻在了你的意识里
It's muscle memory, you've already built it in there.
马嵬尼估算了离他最近和最远目标间的距离
Mawhinney assigns distances to his closest and farthest shots.
你身处的位置决定了你没时间去计算
You're in a position where you don't have time to do an equation
或调整到合适距离  所以只有猜测距离
or get a proper range, then it's range guesstimation.
恰克并没有坐在那里进行计算
Chuck was not sitting there and doing calculations.
而是在"估算"
This was basically "Swagging It".
我们称"瞎猜"的学名叫"估算"
We call a scientific wild ass guess as swag
马嵬尼输入参数也就是调整射距至50码
Mawhinney dials in or "Dopes his scope" for 50 yards:
也就是开始狙杀的距离
point to impact
大概45分钟到1小时后  他们来了
Maybe 45 minutes to an hour later, here they come.
他只身潜伏在一片陌生之地
He's out in the middle of nowhere by himself.
友军在他身后的方向
He's got his friendly forces to his rear
马嵬尼
美军
正前方是敌人  他正处于中间位置
and the enemy to his front, so he's in the middle.
越共军队
马嵬尼
美军
如果越军急速冲过河来
If they rush and get across the river,
他逃脱撤退的机会近乎渺茫
he has very little chance of escaping and evading.
想象一下他们会怎么处置俘虏的狙击手
Imagine what they would do to a sniper if they caught him.
他会被折磨
That would be torture for...
一直到死
forever.
如果情况真的到了这一步
If the situation came to the point that
我深知我们没机会逃脱
I knew we didn't have a chance,
他们朝我们冲过来  我们无路可退
they were coming in on us, there was no way
我会被活捉
I was gonna be taken alive.
北越
南越
亚利桑那属地
北纬15.84度  东经108.06度
南越  1969年情人节
South Vietnam, Valentine's Day, 1969.
海陆狙击手恰克・马嵬尼和他的观察手
Marine sniper Chuck Mawhinney and his spotter
在富邦松河边设下埋伏
set up an ambush along the Phu Bon Song River.
在不足100码之外
Less than 100 yards away,
一个营的北越士兵正朝他们走来
an NVA battalion heads straight for them.
我不是个迷信的人
I was never a real, real religious man,
但当你趴在那而且只有我们两个人时
but when you're laying there and and there's just two of you,
你会变得前所未有地迷信
you can get more religious than you ever thought you could be.
恰克・马嵬尼
前美陆战队狙击手
于是我等到领头的家伙下到
So I wait until the first guy gets up about,
河水齐膝的地方时
just about knee-deep in the water.
我把准星对准他的前额
I've got the reticle right on his forehead.
当他一起身  我扣动了扳机
Just as he gets up, I pull the trigger.
他中弹倒下
And he hits, goes down.
接着我以最快的速度瞄准到下一个目标
And then as fast as I can move from one to the next,
随后就是
it was just pow, pow, pow!
他们不知所措也不知道发生了什么
They don't know what to do and they don't know what's happening.
站在河里发呆
They just froze in the river.
而我就一个接一个地射杀
And I'm just going from one to the next to the next to the next.
你能看到被打飞的帽子
And you can see the hats fly up,
还有在河里倒下的尸体
bodies start going down the river.
我开了16枪
Well, I shot 16 times.
16具尸体倒在河中
16 went down the river.
马嵬尼阻击了敌人
Mawhinney stops the enemy,
却违背了一个狙击手的基本准则
but he violates the sniper's cardinal rule:
在同一位置决不能开火超过两次
never fire more than two shots from a single position.
猎人现在成了被猎杀的对象
The hunter is now the hunted.
我那天晚上开枪过多
That's a lot of shooting at night,
暴露了自己的位置
which tells everybody where you're at.
你能听到子弹朝我们这里飞来
You could hear rounds coming our direction.
我告诉我的搭档  该撤了
I tell my partner, "It's time to get out of here."
我们就边打边撤
So we beat feet back.
30秒内射击16次
16 shots, 30 seconds.
马嵬尼消失在了丛林之中
Mawhinney vanishes into the jungle.
仅一次射击就需要许多复杂步骤
So many things go into making just one shot.
就像交响乐一样  射击有它自己的节奏
It's like its own little symphony.
那一晚  恰克的表现堪称完美
That night, right there and then, Chuck was flawless.
克瑞斯特・杰克  美国海军陆战队
《一枪毙命》作者之一
他演绎了一曲狙击交响乐
He was a symphony.
马嵬尼是怎样成功阻击
How did Mawhinney stop an enemy force
星光瞄准镜
数百倍于己的敌人的
that outnumbered him by hundreds?
一切都要从星光瞄准镜说起
It all starts with the Starlight scope,
一种夜视技术的早期简易版本
a crude early version of night vision technology.
星光瞄准镜下的视野就像模糊的
The Starlight scope is like watching the old fuzzy TV
带天线的老电视的图像
with the bunny ears.
你得摇晃它个六七次才能
You have to, like, shake it six times just to
调出频道  而几秒钟后又没信号了
get the channel to go in and 5 seconds later it's out of focus again.
现在我们的新型AN PVS-10
Where the AN PVS-10, our,
星光瞄准镜                      AN PVS-10瞄准镜
夜视瞄准镜的视野就像高清电视
new night scopes, is like turning on HDTV.
所以能识别目标已经实属不易
So your targets aren't that easily defined.
更难以置信的是
Which is another thing that makes it
他还干掉了这么多敌人
incredible the amount of people he was able to put down.
阴天光线很弱
With the overcast and what little bit of light we did have
透过暴雨  在50到60米的距离上
through that storm, at 50-60 meters,
就已经很难看清
it was really getting really hard to see.
16枪全部命中头部是因为
There were 16 head shots 'cause
那是我唯一能瞄准的部位
that's all I really had to shoot at.
目标
正常人自腰部以上的高度平均为36英寸
The average human being is 36 inches from the waist up.
但马嵬尼只能通过瞄具看到敌人的头部
But Mawhinney can only see the enemy's head through his scope,
目标的尺寸减少到不足10英寸
reducing the target to a mere ten inches.
对于狙击手来说他的射击距离相对较近
He's shooting at a relatively close range for a sniper,
但要考虑到那是在夜晚的条件下
but when you throw in the fact that it's at night
目标也不是静止的而是在运动
and these aren't stationary targets, they're moving.
他需要在目标晃动的情况下
He's got to find that ten inches
瞄准那10英尺的部位
as it moves from left to right, up and down.
之后他得重新再做一遍  循环往复16次
And then he has to do the same thing over again, 16 different times.
这是发生在16个不同位置的16次战斗
So it's 16 different battles and 16 different positions,
绝不能失手  否则死的就是你
and, you can't miss or you're dead.
马嵬尼的M14步枪处于半自动模式
Mawhinney's M14 is in semiautomatic mode.
武器型号：M14半自动步枪
他每1.9秒就击中一个目标
He hits a target every 1.9 seconds.
事先做好计划可以避免低劣的战斗表现
Prior planning prevents piss-poor performance.
如果他那晚用的是雷明顿[指M40]
If he decided to take out the Remington that night,
这会我们也就见不到他了
you would have never been talking about Chuck right now
因为要是这样的话他早已经挂了
'cause he probably would have been killed.
目标的预估对我们来讲很重要
The proximity of the target's very important to us.
那晚  当他在不到100码面对那么多敌人
That night, when he had that many people within a hundred yards,
他首先选对了武器
the choice that he had in his hand was the right choice.
半自动  他能做到两秒一发
Semi-automatic, he could fire a shot every two seconds,
军士长 威廉姆斯・斯凯莱斯
陆战队 武器训练营
不需要再装填就能在短时间内
not reload the weapon and get the most firepower down
发射大量精确火力
accurately as he could in that short amount of time.
栓动式的M40用的是五发的弹仓
The bolt-action M40 has a five-round magazine.
武器型号:M40
而M14是半自动  且用的是20发弹匣
The M14 is semi-automatic and holds 20 rounds.
武器型号:M14
飞出去的子弹越多 对面死掉的也就越多
More rounds downrange faster mean more dead enemy soldiers.
非常规部队中很多人有个概念
A lot of people who are operators explain
叫"行动暴力"
something called "Violence of action."
就是重火力  你我敌对
Massive firepower, you versus me,
我在较近距离用比你强悍的火力压倒你
I'm gonna put you down with massive firepower at a closer range.
恰克那晚上在那种距离上
What Chuck faced that night,
面对的情况是  他必须尽快解决他们
at that range, he had to put 'em down fast.
所以你得从最前的开始  由近及远
That's you start it near to far.
行动暴力
不能先打100码距离上那个
You don't hit somebody at a hundred yards and
再等别人走近  不然他早就到你面前了
work up to the guy close to you, because by then he'd be on you.
所以要像推多米诺骨牌  从最前面开始
So you put 'em down near to far like dominoes falling.
正因如此  那天他们最终都下水喂了王八
Of course they all became good swimmers down the river that night.
行动暴力  这招很实用
Violence of action is a good practice to have.
马嵬尼的每发子弹都以2800尺/秒的速度离膛
Each round Mawhinney fires leaves the muzzle at 2800 feet/s,
外弹道
超过两倍音速
more than twice the speed of sound.
子弹以大约每分钟20万转的速度自转
The bullet rotates at approximately 200,000 revolutions per minute,
击中目标所耗时间少于半秒钟
propelling it into the target in less than half a second.
敌人在听见枪声之前就已经死了
The enemy is dead before he hears the gunshot.
当时就是这么个情况
I was in such a zone.
我把自己想象成子弹来观瞄
I would look through the rifle, but I'm the bullet.
我怎么持枪才能保证我打中目标
Where do I got to hold this rifle to get me where I want to go?
那是当时我脑子里唯一的念头
That was the only thing that was in my mind at that time.
电光火石间尘埃落定  自然而然就这样了
all it is that happens is all at once and, and it just become natural
海陆狙击手学校位于弗吉尼亚匡提科
Marine Scout Sniper School, Quantico, Virginia.
是世界顶尖的几位狙击手的母校
Home to some of the top snipers in the world.
今天  他们当中的一位将会尝试
Today, one of them will try to
重演恰克・马嵬尼的30秒16连发
duplicate Chuck Mawhinney's 16 hits in 30 seconds.
这里是305靶场
This is a range called Range 305.
在这里放置这些气球
Put the balloons up, obviously,
是用爆气球来模拟爆人头
because a shot, balloon busts, the guy is dead.
这些就是马嵬尼当时必须干掉的目标
It simulates this soldier's head that Chuck had to hit.
人的头部大约是10英寸长
A human head is ten inches long,
双手过头顶举着AK47或是别的什么
arms above their heads with their AK-47s,whatever they're carrying
正在涉水
So... and they're wading through the water.
大概是以单兵间距10尺的交错队形前进
they would probably approach in a staggered column about 10 feet apart.
他们得保持较近距离
So they had to be close enough
以便能看到彼此  并通过手势沟通
they still can see each other and give hand-arm signals,
又要有足够间隔   不至被一台机枪全扫了
but far enough that a machine gun won't take the whole gang out.
根据马嵬尼回忆  在大约30秒里
According to Chuck Mawhinney, in around 30 seconds,
他开了16枪
he shot 16 times.
30秒后  16个倒霉蛋就改行
After 30 seconds, there was 16 new human buoys
在河里当浮标了
going down the river.
用这件现代神兵
With this modern-era weapon,
半自动的7.62  还带个很棒的瞄准镜
semiautomatic 7.62 with this awesome scope,
瞄准镜为Schmit&Bender 德国货  号称瞄准镜中的兰博基尼
让我们拭目以待
we're going to see if he can simulate that.
我说"上"  你就开火打第一个
I give the command "Up," Engage the firs t target,
然后你有30秒用16发解决16个目标
and you'll have 30 seconds to engage 16 shots, 16 targets.
射手准备
Shooter, ready.
预备
Stand by.
上
Up!
停火
Cease fire.
15发15中  25秒
15 shots, 15 kills-- 25 seconds.
唯一一个活口  躲在平台后面的紫色气球
The only surviving target: A purple balloon hidden by a berm.
这个紫气球实际上是友军
The lavender balloon was actually a friendly.
他知道  所以就放过它了
He knew that and left him alone.
怀特已经接近马嵬尼了
White nearly matches Mawhinney's sharpshooting,
不过环境还是差了很多
but under far different circumstances.
中士  詹姆斯・怀特
陆战队狙击手
恰克那一战真是惊天地泣鬼神
That's just an amazing feat that Chuck did
因为我这里的目标都是死靶子
'cause these targets were not moving.
我都知道它们在哪
I knew where they were.
它们也没有拿枪对着我
They didn't have guns pointed at me,
我也不是夜间射击
I wasn't laying the re in the middle of the night,
我用的是狙击用的白光镜
and I had the Scout Sniper day scope on there
而不是模糊的老式微光夜视镜
instead of a fuzzy Starlight scope at night, so,
所以他真是很了不起
that's just utterly amazing that he was able to do that.
那天晚上恰克说了  一夫当关
That night, Chuck said, "You know what? I own this river.
万夫莫开
you are not crossing it."
1969年2月14日
February 14, 1969.
那可是情人节
Think about it. St. Valentine's Day.
这是我给北越军的情人节杀杀大礼包
Yeah, my little St. Valentine Day Massacre present to the NVA.
恰克・马嵬尼在越南呆了16个月
Chuck Mawhinney is in Vietnam for 16 months.
确认毙敌103人  可能击杀216人
He racks up 103 kills with 216 probables,
是陆战队史上确认击杀最多的人
giving him the most confirmed kills in Marine Corps history.
人们问我有没有关于越战的噩梦
People have asked me if I had nightmares about Vietnam.
我承认有  但却不是因为某次击杀
Yeah, I have, but never because of a hit.
有次我看见个越共穿过一片稻田
I see a VC walking across the paddy
离我约300米  我给了一个19英寸的提前量
he's about 300 meters from me and I got, like, a 19-inch hold.
我瞄准了预定的地方  扣了扳机
I put it exactly where it should be, squeezed the rifle off.
他转过头来  看着我
And he turned around and he looked at me.
我永生难忘
And that look I'll never forget.
他就那么看了我一眼
He just glared at me.
他的表情我永生难忘
The look in the face never went away.
我看不见我打死的那些人  但我看见了他
I can't... I can't see anybody I shot, but I can see him.
从此我就不得不在余生反复自问
Now I have to think the rest of my life,
他会杀谁  这问题一直困扰着我
"Who'd he kill?" That's the one that haunts me.
35年后  另一名狙击手在一场陆战队史上
35 years later, another sniper fights for his life
最血腥的战斗之一当中浴血
in one of the bloodiest battles in Marine Corps history
狙击手是部队的能量增幅器
Snipers are a force multiplier.
狙击手带观察手就能控制一片区域
You can control an area with just you and your spotter.
我们的击杀率高得吓人
Our shot-to-hit ratio is amazing.
一般的  一个目标平均1.3发
Basically, it's 1.3 rounds per kill.
狙击手的厉害之处是在敌群中播种恐惧的能力
The sniper's main weapon is his ability to induce fear in the enemy,
不仅仅就是打倒一个人
across a much wider group of men
而是能阻吓更多的人
than maybe the one person he's just taken down.
这才真是件厉害的武器
That's a hell of a weapons system.
伊拉克
费卢杰  2004年
Fallujah, 2004.
费卢杰
东经33.3003  北纬43.7717
伊战爆发一年之后  最血腥的战役即将展开
The bloodiest battle of the year-old Iraq War is about to erupt.
四名美国安全承包商遭遇伏击并被虐尸
Four U.S. Security contractors are ambushed and mutilated.
报复来得很快
Revenge is swift.
陆战队开始了"决心警戒行动"
The Marines launch Operation Vigilant Resolve.
我们上尉站在车上  他说
Our captain stood up on a vehicle, and he says,
陆战队员们 这里就是我们的塔拉瓦
"Marines, this is our Tarawa,
均为海陆史上战斗最为惨烈的战区
我们的冲绳  我们的溪山  该我们死战了
this is our Okinawa, this is our Khe Sanh, this is our time.
军士长   威廉姆斯・斯凯莱斯
陆战队 武器训练营
希望费卢杰的野狗饱餐我们死敌的尸体
May the dogs of Fallujah eat hearty off our dead enemy.
这座城我们志在必得
We're gonna take that city on."
瞄准 - 费卢杰
我不管他是耶稣再临
I didn't care if it was the second coming of Christ,
圣诞老人或是复活节兔子  统统靠边
Santa Claus or the Easter Bunny, it didn't matter.
如果他们对我的陆战队兄弟们有威胁
If they were posing a threat to my fellow Marines,
人挡杀人
I was gonna take 'em out.
狙击手
The sniper
伊森・普雷斯
Ethan Place
费卢杰战场  击杀32人
32 kills, Fallujah.
因英勇作战  获银星勋章
Silver star for gallantry.
射杀区域
约朗高地
这是越战以来最激烈的城市作战
In the fiercest urban combat since Vietnam,
21岁的普雷斯是配属到E连的唯一狙击手
the 21-year-old Marine is the only sniper attached to Echo Company.
绝对是一骑当千
It's one man against thousands.
整座城市像西部片里一样
The city was just like the Wild West.
敌众我寡
We were vastly outnumbered.
如果你跟一个陆战队员嚣张
If you mess up as a Marine sniper,
你会上头版头条的
you're gonna be on the front page of the news,
因为你死定了
because you're gonna be killed.
普雷斯的任务是掩护地面的陆战队
Place's mission-- provide cover for the Marines on the ground
消灭敌军战斗人员和火箭推动榴弹小组
and take out enemy fighters and RPG teams.
他是在风口浪尖上
He is at the tip of the spear.
武器:M40A3  陆战队狙击步枪
The weapon: The M40A3, marine sniper rifle.
M40A3的北约弹非常具有破坏性
The M40A3's NATO round is devastating.
武器型号：M40A3
口径: 7.62X51mm
枪口初速: 每秒2550英尺
最远射程: 1000码
在一千码距上
At a thousand yards,
其残余动能比极近距离.357还要高
the bullet has more kinetic energy than a .357 fired at point-blank range.
简而言之  停止力极高
In two words stopping power
作为枪手的猎手  我们用的武器
Being a hunter of gunmen, we use weapons
是彻头彻尾猎杀人专用的
that are built and made to hunt people.
这个步枪型号跟我在费卢杰用的一样
This is the same type of rifle that I used when I was in Fallujah.
这就是陆战队的M40A3狙击步枪
It's the Marine Corp's M40A3 sniper rifle.
尤耐托的瞄镜  10倍率固定
It was a Unertl scope, ten-power fixed.
最大有效射程1000码
Max effective range is a thousand yards.
普雷斯设好了藏身处  或叫最终射击位置
Place sets up his hide, or final firing position,
最终射击位置
显眼地段一幢能俯瞰整条马路的三层楼房
in a prime location,a 3-story building overlooking a long roadway.
他们必须要经过那条主路
They had to move across that main road
才能去路北边找掩护
to get to hides and weapons systems
或是去路北边找武器
that were on the north side of the road,
每当他们要这么做时候  他们都会飞跑
and when they did that, they had to make a dash for their life.
那个时候就是我的机会
That was where you were gonna make your money.
普雷斯通过墙上的弹孔射击  以隐蔽自己的藏身处
Place conceals his location by firing through loopholes,
弹孔
这是城市环境下狙击的重要战术
a key tactic in urban sniping.
屋顶上有一堵五尺高的墙
There was about a five-foot wall on top of the roof,
墙上有我们留下的弹孔
and we'd knocked out little holes
大约有半个篮球大小
that were about half the size of a basketball.
我们就往后移10码建立狙击阵位
Then we'd move back about ten yards and set up a shooting position
这样我们能抢占马路的有利位置
that gave us access to the vantage point of that road.
叛乱分子就会
The insurgents, they would have to
依次进入我视野后才可能开枪
line up directly in my sights to take a shot,
这么一来我倒是轻松多了
which I felt very comfortable in that aspect.
那时候他们对我们唯一有威胁的
The only thing that they had an advantage on us at that time was,
是因为我们没有屋顶
because there was no roof on top,
他们就往我们所在发迫击炮
they would just start dropping mortars.
那时候就只能祈祷打不中了
So you just kind of hope one doesn't have your name on it.
普雷斯和观察手标记射杀区域
Place and his spotter "Range the kill zone,"
也就是给显著地标标记距离
Assigning distances to prominent landmarks and terrain features.
标记射杀区域
进了隐蔽点的第一件事情
One of the first things you do when you get into a hide sight is
就是要做射程卡
you start making a range card,
清楚标记好那些大街上
and really milling out targets and things
能给你瞄准距离提供参考的物件或目标
that you know can provide you with yardage up and down the street.
左边被炸毁的建筑离我525码
Blown-up building on the left is at 525,
525码
300码
打烂掉的汽车离我300码  如此以往
or the shot-up car's at 300, so on and so forth.
普雷斯的观察手负责识别目标和间距
Place's spotter i.D.'s targets and their their distance.
狙击手跟观察手之间
You come up with some type of language
有种特定的沟通语言  用来交流距离
between you and your spotter where you can communicate yards.
比如用棒球场的规矩  可以用些体育术语
You can put it in sectors, you can use sports theory--
比如左外野  中外场
left field, center field--
好让人能够掌握目标的具体位置
to give you an idea of where the target's located.
但当时就是一条笔直的马路  称得上单维
But for us,it was kind of 1-dimensional,straight down an alleyway.
我们那会就用了码数距离标记
And we could just use yard markers at that point.
射杀区域
连起来展现的就是个狙击手的理想国
The targets that it presented was a sniper's dream world.
整个射杀区域长880码
The kill zone is 880 yards long.
我把狙击步枪调节到550码
The range I had my sniper rifle set on was 550 yards.
大约就是场地的中间
It was kind of the center of our kill zone.
当你开始透过瞄镜去看的时候
When you first look down the scope, you can't
禁不住去想那一头是个活生生的人
avoid the fact that it is a human being on the other end of that.
这时候心跳会加快
And that's when your heart starts to race,
这就是人称"扑腾小心肝"的紧张时刻
and you kind of get what they call buck fever.
这个时候就必须要冷静下来
And you have to calm that down and make sure that
重温学过的精确射击培训基本内容
you're going through your fundamentals of marksmanship.
我们受训时总被教导深吸气三次  然后呼气
We were always taught take three big breaths and exhale.
把肺里气都呼出来  但是
You've exhaled all the air out of your lungs and you're not,
战术呼吸
又还没要到吸气的时候
thinking about breathing at that point,
就是人最放松的时刻[即战术呼吸]
that's when you're the most relaxed.
这对于稳定射击平台很有帮助
That's going to keep the most stability in your shooting platform.
扳机控制
一般狙击步枪的扳机扣力约是2.5磅
The trigger pull on most sniper rifles is about 2-and-a-half pounds
只要能保持手指恒定地
So as long as you're consistent with
扣在扳机的同一个位置输出同一个力道
applying that same point of pressure on your finger on that trigger,
就能打得准
you're going to be accurate.
我那会扣扳机扣得都起水泡了
I shot so much that I started getting blisters.
普雷斯牢牢掌握着射杀区域
Place owns the kill zone.
但打偏一发可能就意味着要损失队友
But a missed shot could mean more Marines die on the ground.
他一直守在瞄准镜前
He stays on the scope around the clock.
人说最好只在瞄准镜前看
They say to only be on a scope for
大约30到45分钟  然后就要休息眼睛
about 30 to 45 minutes at a time and then rest your eyes.
可一旦你在伊拉克开了瞄
But when you're in Iraq looking down a scope,
立马就像着了魔一样
it almost becomes something of obsession.
会不想离开瞄镜
You won't come off the scope.
然后就会抓紧每分钟的睡眠时间
And you try to get whatever sleep you can get.
每次就算闭上眼睛了  十字线还在你眼前晃
Anytime you close your eyes, you have a crosshair,
就好象烙在眼球上了一样
which is kind of burned in to your eyeball.
普雷斯的记录  12击杀
Place's kills mount-- 12 dead.
但他面对的是诸多敌人
But he faces an enemy hell-bent
妄图消灭他和他的陆战队弟兄们
on destroying him and his fellow Marines.
叛乱分子开始隔三差五就进行反击
The insurgents started counterattacking about twice a day.
他们开火时身体都暴露在掩体之外
They're very exposed when they're attacking
因为他们老是挑
because they try to take up positions
他们觉得相对安全位置袭击陆战队员们
they feel like are safe to the Marines on the ground,
却不管自己已经暴露了
and that exposes them.
普雷斯的首要目标  解决叛军火箭筒射手
Place's top priority: taking out insurgent RPG gunners.
火箭推进榴弹
[俗称火箭筒]
他们习惯从他们觉得最佳的位置开火
They got comfortable with where they shot the RPGs from,
我们就能在火箭尾焰尽头看到很多目标
We picked up on a lot of targets from the back blast of those rockets.
每次都在同一个位置发射
They would shoot from the same spot,
对于他们  这真不是个好习惯
and that was a bad decision on their part.
普雷斯用的是伏击方式
Place uses the ambush method
狙击手狙击目标时候有两种方式
And there's two ways of engaging a target as a sniper.
一是追踪  就是说
You can track it, which means
把十字线压在目标上跟着走
you put your crosshairs on the target and you follow it.
追踪方式
然后算出合适的提前量再开枪
And you use a proper lead and you shoot it
二就是伏击
or you can ambush it--
伏击方式
就是说你瞄准目标会经过的方向上
you put your scope out in  the direction the target's walking,
等到目标走进视野
and as the target comes into your scope,
就在算好的位置上开火
you fire at the prescribed dope on the weapon.
杀一儆千
"Kill one man, terrorize a thousand."
普雷斯用他的M40A3把火箭筒单位
Place and his M40A3 push RPG teams out
彻底赶出了他们的有效射程
beyond their effective range.
在猎区  他每次扣发
He tightens his grip on the kill zone
都是一记绝杀
with a single, devastating kill shot.
那个目标恰好是515码[471M]
That particular target was right at 515 yards.
515码
普雷斯必须如穿针引线一般
Place must thread the needle, putting a single round
在550米距离一击命中一个10英寸的目标
inside a ten-inch target from five football fields away.
我说  我干掉他了
And I just said, "I got him."
我对着喉咙上部开火
I held right at the upper throat and fired.
直接命中了他的下巴  下嘴唇位置
And that hit right in the lower lip, at the jaw,
打破了他的脸  直接贯穿了他的头
went through his face and out the back of his head.
这是我头一个干净利落的狙杀
That was my first clean kill shot.
生理机能瞬间停止
It's instantaneous incapacitation.
世间不再有那么个人
its just seized to exist
没有犹豫  没有不忍  就这样
no flinching, no nerve bendings, its over
要瞄准人的致命T区
You aim for what they call "The Fatal T,"
致命T区
简而言之就是瞄脑干打
And it's to aim for brain's stem base clean.
要是能击中该区域  那人倒地前就已经死了
If you can hit that, he's going to die before he hits the ground.
那会切断整个中枢神经的信号传递
It's going to cut off all signals to the body.
在那片区域我干掉了19个人
I'd had over 19 kills in that area.
尸体就那么留在街上
The dead bodies would lay out in the street,
很多野狗就以那些尸体为食
and there's a lot of wild dogs and they would feed on the bodies.
我坚信  对于叛乱分子这很有震撼力
And that had a devastating affect, I'm sure, to the insurgents,
眼看着自己战友倒在大街上被野狗啃咬
seeing their friends laying out in street getting chewed on by dog
我刚来的时候  有人跟我说
When I first arrived, someone said,
军士长  过来看看这个
"Hey, First Sarge, come take a look at this."
我透过射击孔看了看
And I looked through his loophole
看到了八具尸体  是敌人的
and I saw eight bodies-- dead bodies of our enemy--
说明无论敌人在玩什么花样  都不能得逞
that, uh, whatever they're trying to do wasn't working,
我回过头看着普雷斯下士  他就笑了笑说
and looking back at Corporal Place, he just kind of smiled and said,
份内活  应该的
"Just doing my job."
人常说狙击手是增幅器
People say snipers are a combat multiplier.
他牢牢掌握着那片区域
He owned that whole area.
击毙19人
19 kills.
普雷斯的神射帮助了陆战队继续深入推进
Place's sharpshooting allows Marines to push further into the city.
战斗依然残酷
But the battle still rages.
他经历的最致命最高难度的战役即将来到
His most difficult and deadly shot is yet to come.
远在狙击手上战场开枪之前
Long before the sniper pulls the trigger on the battlefield,
他必须在靶场上掌握各种绝杀技巧
he must master the art of the kill shot on a firing range.
考核用的是靶纸  纸是死的人是活的
We'd qualify on these inanimate pieces of paper.
是人就会动
Everyone that's a human being moves.
一旦动了 要打中就很难
It's hard enough to hit somebody when he's like this.
军士长 威廉姆斯・斯凯莱斯
陆战队 武器训练营
没人喜欢上来就打移动靶
No one's gonna be like this for you and say, "Go ahead."
所以我们强调针对核心区域  来解决目标
That's why we focus on the core,right here, and put him down.
模拟场景
是人就想打出完美一击
You want to get that perfect shot,
但除非你能命中关键脏器
but if you can hit anywhere in the vital organs,
那才是绝杀
it's gonna be a kill shot.
伊拉克
费卢杰  2004年
Fallujah, 2004.
费卢杰
东经33.3003  北纬43.7717
狙击手  伊森・普雷斯
The sniper: Ethan Place.
四天  击毙19人
Four days, 19 kills.
死尸满大街
Dead bodies litter the street,
给了叛乱分子一个警告  不听话你就是下一个
a warning to insurgents: you could be next.
弹药  7.62北约弹
The ammo: 7.62 Nato rounds,
精度和停止力的完美组合
a deadly combination of accuracy and stopping power.
我们的狙击弹药是7.62X51mm
Our sniper round is 7.62 by 51,
比5.56MM的各型烧药更多
which means it has more powder and
而且"子弹更得劲"  我们用的是175格令的弹头
it has more "Ass to the round." We use a 175-grain round,
伊森・普雷斯
前海陆狙击手
这是相对较重的弹头
and that's a fairly heavy round.
弹头越重  停止力就越多
The heavier the grain you go,the more knockdown power it's gonna have
因为是更大的弹头打到了人身上
'cause it's a big round that's impacting that person.
终端弹道有两种效果
You have two aspects of terminal ballistics:
终段弹道
・侵彻效应
・空腔效应
侵彻效应和空腔效应
the crush factor and the tear factor of the round.
侵彻效应在于
The crush factor being
侵彻效应
弹头直接作用于身体组织的侵彻杀伤
what the round's gonna eliminate from body
以及它所形成贯通伤道  像这个伤道
and it's gonna pass out, like the exit hole
出口有50分硬币大小
probably the size of a half-dollar.
伤口喷出来的组织是被弹头撕裂挤压粉碎的
The tissue that gets blown out of the body that's just crushed.
空腔杀伤则是指弹丸在人体内时
Then you have a tear factor, which is the tissue
将人体组织撕开造成的杀伤
that is torn by the projectile when it's in, the body.
空腔效应
空腔会有12到18英寸[30-46cm]的深度
The tear factor could be 12 to 18 inches in length,
造成的损伤会非常严重
The damage it's gonna cause, it's gonna be absolutely devastating.
普雷斯的绝杀把叛乱分子又逼回了暗处
Place's kill shots push insurgents back into the shadows.
纵是如此他们也无处藏身
But there is nowhere to hide.
距离就是狙击手的优势
Distance is the sniper's ally.
遗憾的是对于叛乱分子
Unfortunately for a lot of the insurgents,
我们一开火  他们就会往远处退
when we start engaging them, they would move back.
但其实在五百码上开枪造成的杀伤效应
If we hit them at 500 yards, it was having higher killing effects
要比二三百码上来得更严重
than at 200 or 300 yards, even.
经验法则证实  距离越近
The rule of thumb is that the closer they are,
弹头的速度最高
the bullet's moving at a faster pace, so it's-
杀伤就不够理想
it's not gonna do as much damage.
弹头不在身体里停止  就没把动能全部传递出去
但当他们退远了之后
And as they back off a little bit,
子弹速度不再那么快了
the round's not going too fast.
一头扎进身体里
It just zips through the body.
然后在身体内扩张得更大
It's gonna be able to expand a little bit in the body
造成更多创伤
and cause more damage.
决心警戒行动  第五日
Operation Vigilant Resolve, day five.
费卢杰
战斗日趋激烈  普雷斯更加深入城区
Fighting intensifies and Place pushes further into the city.
他换了一处屋顶紧盯一条叛乱分子的
He takes the fight to the enemy from a new rooftop hide
武器补给线  继续追着敌人打
overlooking a major supply line for insurgent weapons.
东经 33.386069  北纬 43.759543
第二个位置上
The second position,
我们就直接对着一条主要街道
we were looking directly down at a main alleyway.
有很多小街道与之连通
It had a bunch of small alleyways connecting to it
叛乱分子必须不断穿行才能推进和撤退
The insurgents would have to cross to get movement back and forth.
人跑动的速度有时候真的惊人
You'd be surprised how fast some of those guys can run.
我们常开玩笑说  跑得慢的都死光了
We used to joke that the slow ones are all gone.
剩下的都是在食物链顶端的了
So anybody that's left is-is the top of the food chain.
他们真的很快  像风一样
They were fast. They ran like the wind.
这类目标被称为"有限暴露目标"
We call it "Limited exposure targets."
有限暴露目标
400-500码距上是很难打中一个
Very difficult to hit a running man at 400, 500 yards,
极速穿越街道的人  试着追踪也难
crossing an alley, and try and track him.
几近不可能
Almost impossible.
普雷斯是以解决这些跑动靶出名的
Place was famous for hitting those guys on a dead sprint.
一发不中意味着更多的海陆兄弟会有危险
A missed shot means an insurgent lives on to fight and kill more Marines
在同胞的生命有危险的情况下  普雷斯遇到了
With American lives at stake, Place is confronted with
一个令狙击手最头疼的高难度狙击之一
one of the most difficult shots a sniper will ever face.
他只有不到两秒来击倒疯狂逃命的敌人
He has less than two seconds to hit a man on a dead run,
还是在相隔660米的距离上
six football fields away.
有个穿白袍的男的  穿着拖鞋
There was man in a white outfit, sandals on,
带着AK-47  探头探脑偷看好一会了
AK-47, and he'd been turkey-peeking back and forth.
他正透过一扇
He was looking through a black door
敞开着的黑门观察着
that they had that was swung open outside a house.
我觉得他没意识到
And I don't think he understood
我能看见他的头和他拿的什么武器
that we could see his head and could identify a weapon.
在他起跑横穿的时候
Right as he started to dash across,
我就已经瞄好了
I was able to get a good mil-hold, fire
打出了膛中的子弹
and the round carried and hit him
直接命中了他的脸部上方
right in the upper part of the face.
这是瞬间机能停止击杀
It was immediate incapacitation shot,
他倒地前就已经死了
killed him before he hit the ground.
不到两秒
In less than two seconds,
普雷斯干掉了600码距上逃命的叛乱分子
Place takes out the sprinting insurgent from 600 yards.
这种类型的射击最难之处
Well, the most difficult thing about those type of shots
提前量
在于计算物体当时的运动速度
is trying to guess the speed in which the target's target's moving.
常见目标速度在8.6M/H[13.84Km/H]
The average sprinting target moves at 8.6 miles per hour.
目标速度
8.6M/H
要补足这个差距  普雷斯必须要
To compensate for this, Place must
瞄在他跑动方向前方的一段距离上
aim several feet in front of the running insurgent.
这就是所谓的提前量
this is known as Leading the Target
要打移动靶
If we have a running target,
不能把瞄准线的中心十字压在目标靶上
you're not holding the crosshairs of the reticle on the target,
而是要根据单体跑动方向的不同
so the reticle may be to the right or the left of the individual,
准心应适当偏左或是偏右
depending upon where they're running.
这样当你扣下扳机后
And when you squeeze the trigger,
他们就是在往你打出的子弹上跑
they're gonna basically run into the bullet.
那个距离即提前量  是用密位来表示的
The distance, or lead, is measured in mils.
密位点
21英寸
600码距上  一个密位大概代表21英寸
At 600 yards, one mil represents roughly 21 inches.
我当时针对跑过街的目标给出的提前量
The lead that I led the individual that was coming across the street
是在右方4.5个密位左右
was right at about four-and-a-half mils,
相当大的了
which is a-- that's a pretty, big lead.
再大的话
Anything more than that,
瞄准镜就没办法了
you're really stretching the capabilities of the scope.
600码距上4.5密位
A four-and-a-half- mil lead at 600 yards
相当于在目标前的八尺
means Place must aim eight feet in front of the target.
八尺
两尺
偏了一个密位  就是偏了两英尺[61CM]
If he's off by one mil, he misses by two feet.
以2550尺每秒的速度
Traveling at 2,550 feet per second,
175格令的弹头钻入颅腔
the 175-grain round enters the cranial cavity,
在150万分之一秒内切断了脑干
severing the brain stem in one-half millionth of a second.
我在观察镜里看到了这下  砰
In my scope, I witnessed that one shot-- boomp.
人倒下了  枪也掉了  一动不动
This lump of crap fell, weapon fell, no movement.
他就是这般致命
That's how deadly he was.
从此再没人敢从那位置出来
And no one ever came out of that position again.
20天  击杀32人
30 days, 32 kills.
伊森・普雷斯在费卢杰扮演了重要角色
Ethan Place plays a critical role in the fight for Fallujah.
他的神射挽救了无数海陆同袍
His sharpshooting saves countless Marines
并把恐慌的阴影带给了叛乱分子和火箭筒队
and wreaks havoc on insurgent fighters and RPG teams.
他们走上谈判桌
When they came to the negotiation table,
第一件事就是要求撤出所有的狙击手
one of the first things they wanted was the snipers to be pulled back.
固然是因为我们消灭威胁很在行
We were extremely effective at eliminating threats.
更因为我们的子弹神出鬼没
But the ability not to know where or when it's coming,
那真是让他们很绝望
uh, just was devastating on them.
他获得了银星勋章
He received a Silver Star.
这位先生帮了我们连很大忙
That gentleman saved our bacon a lot,
他始终掌握那个区域
but he owned that whole area.
海陆狙击手学校  弗吉尼亚州  匡提科
Marine Sniper School-- Quantico, Virginia.
那次费卢杰600码绝杀之后5年
Five years after his 600-yard kill shot in Fallujah,
伊森・普雷斯与军士长比尔・斯凯尔斯重聚首
Ethan Place reunites with Sergeant Major Bill Skiles
试着再现当日辉煌
to try and duplicate the feat.
这里零度以下的环境跟在伊拉克截然相反
The subfreezing conditions are the extreme opposite of those in Iraq,
对这位前狙击手来说是很大的挑战
providing the ultimate test for the former sniper.
这里是弗吉尼亚匡提科  600码距线
We're at the 600-yard line here in Quantico, Virginia.
准备用600码距上的两个正面靶
Trying to simulate down the range of 600 yards of
模拟当时街道两旁的建筑
two target  fronts that simulates parts of buildings,
并再现当时的敌人穿越的情景
and to simulate how our enemy would run across our lines
身后这位一级棒的美国人
and this great American behind you
会用子弹截停标靶给你看
would intercept them sometimes with bullets.
准备好了没
You ready?
好得不能再好
Ready as one can be.
手指都没感觉了
Can't feel my fingers.
跟费卢杰大不同吧
Little different from, uh, Fallujah, huh?
是
Yeah.
那里可没下雪
Sure it wasn't snowing there
在伊拉克  普雷斯的作业环境都是华氏120度以上
In Iraq, Place worked in temperatures in excess of 120 degrees.
高温下弹丸速度更快  打得更远
Hotter rounds flew further and faster.
现在  普雷斯的射击环境也很复杂
Here, Place's shot is complicated by
气温低于华氏0度  风速达每小时15英里
subfreezing temperatures and a 15-mile-per- hour wind.
风速
15英里\小时
他开始校准将步枪的弹着点调整至600码
He gets on target or zeroes his rifle for 600 yards point of impact.
长时间暴露于高温或寒冷环境下
Prolonged exposure to heat or cold
校准步枪
子弹的角分  即弹道属性会有重大改变
can alter a bullet's minute of angle, or trajectory.
600码距  20度温差足以增加空气密度
At 600 yards,20-degree drop in temperature can increase air density
从而导致弹丸向下偏离6英寸
causing a bullet to miss its target low by six inches.
对于狙击手  这一偏差足以决定生死
For a sniper, that could be the difference between life and death.
现在  我来为他报告风速风向
Now, I will call his wind for him.
我们要模拟一个在两建筑之间跑动的人
We're gonna simulate a running man between the two target frames.
首先从右向左开始
We're gonna go right to left first,
然后从左向右  来回几次再交换
then left to right, do a couple passes each.
为防预判  我们增加了变化
can't just lead, so we get his hits
与在费卢杰相似  普雷斯将只有
Just like Fallujah, Place will have less than
不到两秒时间射击600码之外的目标
two seconds to hit the target at 600 yards.
开始放靶
Go ahead and run them.
准备就绪
Stand by.
可以放靶
Go ahead and start running.
从子弹消失的轨迹来看
By the vapor trail, looked like
子弹似乎从他右肩上掠过
it appeared to be-- went over his right shoulder.
普雷斯偏离了目标身后仅几英寸
Place misses just behind the target by a few inches.
准备下一枪  上一枪他预判目标从右向左
This time,he was supposed to come right to left last time.
现在如我所料他继续预判从右向左
Now he's gonna go right to left like I wanted.
风速
17英里\小时
风速渐起  增加了普雷斯第二枪的难度
The wind picks up, complicating Place's second shot.
他必须减少提前量
He must decrease his lead so
不至于射偏到目标前方
he doesn't miss wide in front of the target.
这枪提前量增加3个密位  可以吗
Get about a three-mil lead this time, all right?
因为上一枪瞄得太靠后了
'Cause you're trailing a little bit.
正中靶心
正中靶心  伊森你看到没
You're dead center, Ethan-- you see it?
是的
Yeah.
正中靶心  伙计们
That was dead center, guys.
仅用时1.3秒  普雷斯正中目标胸部
In 1.3 seconds, Place hits the target in the chest.
一枪也许是走运  再打一枪看看
Hey, one shot's lucky-- do it again.
让他们放靶  你再打一枪
Tell them to pull it out so you can do it again.
右边
Right edge.
开始放靶
Go ahead and run it.
风速稳定
Wind's good.
由于目标从相反方向开始运动
With the target moving in the opposite direction,
普雷斯增加提前量补偿风速造成的偏差
Place increases his lead to compensate for the wind.
肾脏部位
命中
A hit
这类目标被称为"有限暴露目标"
Again, it's called Limited Exposure Targets.
在战场上  有许多我们的敌人
Overseas, we had many of our bad guys
试图冲过火线来运送武器弹药  补给
that want to run or sprint across with supplies, with weaponry.
有时只暴露一两秒钟的时间
Sometimes we only have a one-second, two-second exposure.
这一次他出现然后开始冲刺
That time, he came up, started sprinting.
600码外伊森在第一秒就干掉了他
Ethan knocked him down in the first second at 600 yards.
射中了他的肾脏
Got him in the kidney.
干得好
Toast.
两发两中  太棒了
Two hits, two shots. That's awesome.
退弹
Unload.
威风不减当年
It's like old times.
第二枪的感觉相当好
Well, the second one felt real good.
你感觉怎样
How you doing?
很好
Good.
你看这里我的第一枪  正中靶心
You see up here the first shot that I hit was dead on.
质心
在600码的距离上  绝对是致命一击
It was 600 yards. That'll be a devastating kill.
估计没一两分钟那家伙就死了
Probably take just a minute or two for them to pass away,
但第二枪  我打得有些偏
but the second shot, I was a little off.
风速对我有一点影响
Uh, the wind probably effected it a little bit.
肾脏上部
这一枪有点偏  不过击中了肾脏上部
It was a little bit of a trail shot, but it'd be more upper kidney shot,
在这一距离上仍足以致命
and that's still gonna be a devastating shot at those ranges.
目标没你希望的那样密集  但设想一下
Not the tightest group you'd hope for, but still, at the same time,
两枪皆致命  你还是击杀2个目标
considering, two kill shots, you're still gonna have two kills.
他精确射击的基本功没有退化
His fundamentals of marksmanship, he has not lost it.
他的基本功从枪械到肩膀乃至整个躯干
His own fundamentals of weapon to shoulder, and his own body,
包括他的呼吸  脉搏
his breathing, his pulse,
他对瞄准  提前量和击发时机的掌握
his delivery, his eyes, his lead--
他仍然出类拔萃
that's what is phenomenal, he still has.
好想念这种味道
I miss that smell a lot.
就这么点爱好
Love that.
一上瘾就戒不掉
Gets addicting, and you miss it.
离开费卢杰战火弥漫的街巷  回到越南战场
From the war-torn streets of Fallujah to the killing fields of Vietnam,
一代传奇狙击手与其死敌针锋相对
a legendary sniper goes head-to-head with a deadly foe.
应该说  我开枪是最快的
By looks of things, I was just the quickest on the trigger.
否则被干掉的就是我了
Otherwise, he'd have killed me.
以下节目含有暴力情节  不适合青少年观众
请慎重观看
敌方狙击手是我的梦魇  因为
My worst nightmare is an enemy sniper, and the reason for that is,
狙击手是战场上最致命的武器
a sniper is the most deadly weapon on the battlefield.
他可以埋伏一整天
He can wait there all day.
时机若未出现
The situation doesn't present itself,
他明天还会再来
he comes back tomorrow to get you.
他只需赌赢一次即可
He only has to get lucky once.
可以这样讲  这是军人之间的
The bottom line is, it's the ultimate challenge
终极对决
as far as soldiering is concerned.
一对一的决斗
It's just you against somebody else.
猎杀眼镜蛇
越南  1966年
Vietnam, 1966.
我其实并不喜欢杀人
I really didn't like to kill.
模拟场景
但当你深入险境去寻歼一个
But to pit myself against another living, breathing human being
与你旗鼓相当的狙击手时
who could kill me just as quick as I could him--
这才称得上是挑战
that was the challenge of it.
狙击手  卡洛斯・哈斯库克  海军陆战队传奇射手
The sniper: Carlos Hathcock, Marine Corps legend.
狙击手
卡洛斯・哈斯库克
确认毙敌93人
海军陆战队传奇
射杀区域  55号高地
The hunting ground: Hill 55.
北越
南越
55号高地
北纬  15.92度  东经  108.16度
我们已歼灭了那一区域大部分敌方狙击手
We had eliminated most of the enemy snipers in that area.
爱德华・J・兰德
前美国海军陆战队少校
情报部的同事告诉我们
The intelligence folks had told us that
有个家伙被派来挑战我们
someone was being sent down to challenge us.
仅知其代号为  眼镜蛇
The sniper is known only as The Cobra.
若能击毙哈斯库克  他就能得到3万美元赏金
If he kills Hathcock, he collects a $30,000 bounty.
北越专程派个狙击手来杀我
This North Vietnamese sniper was sent down there to get me,
卡洛斯・哈斯库克  1983年采访资料片段
这让我很不爽
which I really didn't appreciate.
眼镜蛇游弋于55号高地附近
The Cobra stalks Hill 55,
那是陆战队1师狙击学校的大本营
home base for the 1st Division Marine Scout, Sniper School.
这一枪是他向哈斯库克下的战书
With one shot, he issues a challenge to Hathcock:
出来一决高下
Come and get me.
对方敢把枪杆子伸我家门口来
The killer gunner's setting right outside my door of my hooch.
结果就是被我送上西天
And, uh, I watched him die.
我发了毒誓要干掉他  不惜一切
Took a vow, right then, I was gonna get him somehow or another.
他在离我们营地1000码的地域活动
He was operating about 1,000 yards outside the wire.
他会沿运河顺流而下
He would come down a canal.
借着黑暗进入到狙击位置
During low light, he would crawl into his position.
就是他设埋伏的地方
That's where he was living, hanging his hat.
卡洛斯要去那把他毙了
Carlos wanted to go to get him.
那一枪之后  我叫上我的搭档约翰・伯克
When he started shooting, I got John Burke, who was my partner,
我们一起去猎杀他
and we went out, and out-trailed him.
他是个很机敏很聪明的家伙
Very cagey, very smart individual.
我意识到他也很高杆
And I figured he was close to being as good as I was,
仅次于我了
but there ain't no way.
毫无疑问我才是最棒的
Ain't nobody that good.
哈斯库克和伯克一连追踪了眼镜蛇两天
Hathcock and Burke track the Cobra for two days.
他们在泥地上发现了许多脚印
They discover muddy footprints
并继续向丛林腹地深入
and push deeper into the jungle.
一场生死攸关的猫鼠游戏悄然开始
A deadly game of cat and mouse, is underway.
人云  以毒攻毒  以暴制暴
They say it takes a crook to catch a crook.
以狙击手来消灭狙击手
It takes a sniper to neutralize a sniper.
一个了解敌手
The sniper that knows more about his enemy
马克・斯宾塞
英军退役军士长
远胜于对方了解自己的狙击手
than his enemy knows about him,
才是这场生死游戏的最终赢家
he is gonna be the man that wins
哈斯库克寻找着眼镜蛇留下的蛛丝马迹
Hathcock looks for signs of the Cobra.
从折断的树枝到踏过的草地
Anything from broken twigs and grass
再从脚印到碾过的青苔
to footprints and crushed lichen.
这是追猎  即人员追踪的基本要领
Basic elements of the hunt, or man-tracking.
人员追踪
狙击手都接受过寻找蛛丝马迹的训练
Snipers are trained to find the minute details.
哪怕是一片区域的颜色异常
If there is just the wrong color,
伴有成簇的树叶
within a certain area of foliage,
狙击手也需要查个一清二楚
you've got to start asking yourself why is that.
这极有可能是敌方狙击手露出的马脚
And that could be the one thing that gives the sniper away.
每一丝风吹草动  甚至气味
Every breeze, every insect, every smell
都要察觉到并加以思索
immediately goes into your computer, your mind,
你要有能力去分析这些
and you're able to analyze it
并作出判断  得出结论
and come up with a decision as to what it means.
对卡洛斯  这几乎成为了他的本能
In Carlos's case, he was able to do that almost instinctively.
眼镜蛇的行踪有些过于暴露了
The tracks left by the Cobra are a little too obvious.
哈斯库克察觉到了圈套
Hathcock smells a trap.
他和伯克以狙击手低身位匍匐前进
He and Burke drop into a sniper low crawl,
狙击手低身位
每次前进4英寸
moving forward four inches at a time.
你所做的每一件事必须经过深思熟虑
Everything you do has to be extremely well thought out,
然后缓慢地施行
and normally very slowly carried out.
追猎向丛林深处发展
The hunt moves further into the jungle.
哈斯库克深知就在前方某处
Hathcock knows that somewhere out there,
眼镜蛇正严阵以待
the Cobra is watching and waiting.
气氛会十分紧张
There is that heightened tension.
那种无形的压力不断折磨着你的神经
There's an inbuilt level of stress that is constantly there.
你的感官似乎突然灵敏起来
Your senses are kind of heightened.
你会比从前对声音更为敏感
You're listening harder than maybe you would do before.
当两个优秀的狙击手互相寻歼对方时
If you've got another professional that's hunting you down,
这其实就是一场谁先犯错的博弈
and it really is a competition of who's gonna make the first mistake,
以及你的失误是否暴露给了对方
and whether you're in a position to spot that mistake.
眼镜蛇出洞了
The Cobra is on the move.
他偷偷潜过哈斯库克右翼试图伏击
He sneaks around Hathcock's right flank for an ambush.
两个顶尖狙击手在不断试图
It was the case of two very, very good soldiers
猜透对方的企图
constantly trying to outthink each other.
一条折断的树枝暴露了眼镜蛇的位置
A snapped twig gives away the Cobra's position.
哈斯库克和伯克迅速寻找掩护
Hathcock and Burke sprint for cover.
接下来  哈斯库克犯了一个错误
The next mistake is made by Hathcock.
几乎使他葬送了性命
It nearly gets him killed.
我从一棵朽木上跌了下来  他开了枪
I fell in an old rotted tree, and he made a shot.
伯克和我都以为他自己中弹了
Burke and I both thought he was hit.
我发现他水壶被打了个洞
I noticed a hole in his canteen.
我说  你没事  知道吗
I said, "You ain't hurt. You know?
你没受伤  不过你水壶开花了
"You ain't hurt. This just killed a devil bloody canteen, that's all."
没等哈斯库克还击
Before Hathcock can return fire,
眼镜蛇消失在了丛林之中
the Cobra vanishes into the jungle.
他一路狂奔
He started running.
坏蛋夹着尾巴逃了  就是这样
The bad guy started running.Yeah.
我们继续四处搜索
And we moseyed around and mangled around,
我们运动到了他原来的位置
and we worked around to where I was in his old spot.
他也来到了我之前的位置
He was in my old spot.
两个狙击手之间只有不到300码的距离
Less than 300 yards separate the snipers.
猎手和猎物最终正面对决
The hunter and the hunted are finally face to face.
那时候正好是下午
By then-- it was afternoon--
对他有所不利  因为他面朝太阳
which was a bad thing for him, 'cause he was facing the sun.
我猜是阳光射到他的镜片上闪了一下
The sun glinted off his lens of his scope, I guess.
于是我朝闪光处开了枪
I shot it where the glint was.
时机恰到好处
It just happened to be the right time.
就当时而言  我开枪的速度是最快的
By the looks of things, I was just the quickest on the trigger.
否则  死的就是我了
Otherwise, he'd have killed me.
我是怎么知道他有机会杀我的
How do I know he would have killed me?
因为我一枪打穿了他的瞄准镜
'Cause I shot right through his scope,
直直穿过他的瞄准镜  连镜壁都没碰
right straight through his scope, didn't touch the sides.
空心穿过
Didn't touch the sides.
他没能抓住机会杀我  那他也就没机会活命了
He didn't do it in our side, no good in his side either.
这枪正中右眼  连右半个脑袋也打掉了
Yeah, it hit him in the eye and took off the right side of his head.
距离300码  哈斯库克一枪
At 300 yards, Hathcock fired directly
正中眼镜蛇的苏制PU瞄准镜
into the Cobra's Soviet-made PU scope.
这种情形只有当两名狙击手的枪
The shot is only possible if both snipers' weapons
径直瞄准对方时才有可能出现
are pointing directly at one another.
那个瞄准镜口径大概有25美分硬币大小
I would say the scope was about the size of a quarter.
长度约5英尺半  钢制镜身
Those scopes were about five and a half inches long, steel body,
苏制PU瞄准镜
仅由一组物镜和目镜构成
and they're just an objective lens and an observation lens.
一道敌人物镜反射出的阳光
It came down to a reflective light ray off the enemy's objective lens.
原因可能很简单  由于疲劳
That could have been something as simple as fatigue
或者片刻的分神
or just a momentary lapse of concentration
使他忘记了阳光照射的不断移动
where he forgot to focus on the fact that the sun is constantly moving.
万里挑一的经典狙杀
One-in-a-million shot.
他击中敌人并不稀奇
It's not dumb luck that he hit the enemy,
经典的是他一枪穿过了敌人的瞄准镜
but for it to go down the scope was just luck.
43年后  另一名海军陆战队狙击手准备再现
43 years later, another Marine sniper sets out to replicate
卡洛斯・哈斯库克这万里挑一的一击
Carlos Hathcock's one-in-a-million shot.
美国田纳西州孟菲斯  T1G战术训练基地
狙击手史蒂夫・瑞切特  美国海军陆战队退役上士
The sniper: Staff sergeant Steve Reichert, US MC Retired.
这个假人名叫死鬼弗雷德
Our mannequin's name is Dead Fred.
T1G基地CEO
前海军陆战队上士  Steve Reichert
我们想做一次射击试验
What we're trying to do is set up a shot
模拟卡洛斯・哈斯库克在越南那一枪
simulating what Carlos Hathcock did in Vietnam,
将子弹射穿瞄准镜
where he sent his round on through the scope,
然后打进目标的脑袋
into the brain housing group.
史蒂夫用的是海军陆战队M40A1狙击步枪
Steve is using the M40A1 Marine sniper rifle.
.308口径雷明顿枪弹
The round is Remington .308 caliber.
这种子弹在1,000码处的动能
This round, at 1,000 yards,
比.357在抵近射击位置射击时还大
has more kinetic energy than a .357 at point blank.
瞄准镜应在他眼睛前方约3英寸处
So this needs to be about three inches in front of his eye.
这家伙有点僵硬
Guy's got a little bit of rigor mortis.
瑞切特距目标30码
Reichert is at 30 yards,
与哈斯库克300码的射距相比
but the difference in the speed of the round
子弹速度差别不大  可以忽略不计
is negligible from Hathcock's 300-yard shot.
子弹将以近2,550英尺每秒的速度击中瞄准镜
The bullet will hit the scope at nearly 2,550 feet per second.
准备就绪
Going hot.
瑞切特将试射各种瞄准镜
Reichert will experiment with various scopes
并比较每次射击的子弹轨迹与终端弹道
to compare the flight path and terminal ballistics of each shot.
瑞切特的第一个标靶是个可调倍率瞄准镜
Reichert's first target is a modern-day variable power scope.
子弹没有从另一端射出来
Eh, it didn't come out the back end.
里面有一些子弹碎片
There's some bullet fragments, there.
看上去子弹是留在瞄准镜内了
It appears to be the bullet actually stopped inside the scope.
这里也有一些子弹碎片
There's still some bullet fragments in there.
看来当子弹射中第一片镜片时
So as that bullet hit the first lens,
它大概就开始变形破裂
it probably started to jag, started to tear off.
弹头的铅核开始碎裂
The lead core started to rip up.
如果你是瞄准镜后面那家伙
If you were the guy behind that scope right now,
此刻大概会有一脸的碎玻璃和一个黑眼圈
you'd probably have a lot of glass in your face and a black eye,
不过还活着  还能再上战场
but you'd live to fight another day.
一枪  一个黑眼圈
One shot, one black eye.
瑞切特又安好一个瞄准镜  要再试一次
Reichert sets up another scope for a second attempt.
第二枪也没能击穿瞄准镜
The second shot fails to make it through the scope.
我们刚才打的是两个现代的变倍瞄准镜
The scopes we're shooting now are modern variable power scopes.
里面有更多的镜片
They have a lot more lenses,
以及更多的内部构件
basically a lot more internal components.
那次卡洛斯射穿的瞄准镜
The scope Carlos shot into that day
苏制PU瞄准镜
只有大概一两个镜片  不像这两个瞄准镜那么多
probably had one or two lenses but not as many as these scopes.
当子弹击中第一片玻璃时
When that round hits the first piece of glass,
弹头就开始变形
it's going to start to deform the bullet.
我们用的这枚全金属被甲弹
It's a full metal jacket like we just shot--
遇到了更多阻力  受到更多物体的阻挡
encountered more resistance, impacted more objects,
来到这里时
came back here,
击穿了更多镜片  此时弹丸速度已经很慢了
hit more lenses, and by then it was traveling slow enough
以至无法再击穿后端的玻璃了
not to even break the glass on the back end.
我们换个现代的内红点瞄准镜再试一次
We'll try it again with a, a modern red dot scope.
在尺寸和内部结构上
In size and internal setup,
它与哈斯库克射穿的PU瞄准镜十分相似
it's very similar to the PU scope Carlos Hathcock shot through
也许在中间会多一个镜片
with the addition of maybe one extra lens right in the center.
这次用这个瞄准镜  也许我们运气会好些
We might have better luck with this scope.
这次好像行了
That one looked like it worked.
子弹击中第一个镜头  破碎不算太厉害
It hit the first lens, broke up not too much,
外壳有些开裂
the jacket started to come apart,
射穿第二个镜片后击中眼睛上部
punched out the second lens and right above the eye.
你可以看出  弹头铅核基本完好
You can see that the lead core was pretty much intact.
它贯穿了头部
It went through the head.
从后脑射出后继续飞行
Punched through the head on the back end here, kept on going.
这家伙肯定死翘了
This guy would be more than dead.
如果这是个真人
If this would have been a real person,
他的颅内组织会喷溅而出  我们称之为爆头
he would have complete cranial evacuation. We call it a canoe.
基本上他的脑袋会开花
Basically his head would have popped open
而此刻我大概能直接往他脖子里看了
and I'd probably be looking straight down his neck right now.
是啊  一塌糊涂
Yeah, a little bit messy.
卡洛斯碰到的那个PU瞄准镜和这个类似
The scope he encountered-- the PU scope-- it was similar to this,
而他又是个神射手
and Carlos being an outstanding marksman,
在这次试射之后我确信无疑
I have no doubt after doing this that
卡洛斯那一枪绝对是可行的
the shot Carlos pulled off was definitely doable.
一枪  击破瞄准镜  击毙眼镜蛇
One shot, one shattered scope, one dead Cobra.
这是哈斯库克传奇人生中的又一辉煌
Another chapter in the legendary life of Carlos Hathcock.
这并非取人性命的艺术
It isn't the art of taking someone's life.
对我来说  这关乎能救多少陆战队员的性命
To me it's how many Marines we can save.
如果你有可能对我们造成危害
We will pick the time and place to do harm to you
我们会择机先干掉你
if you have premonition to do harm to us.
第一次对准活人扣动扳机时
First time I pulled the trigger on a live person,
我从没有考虑过结果
I never thought about the consequences.
当时就是怕搞砸了
I was basically just afraid not to screw up.
我不能射失目标
I didn't want to miss.
那可是实战的场合
This is a live situation.
如果我搞砸了  战友就会送命
If I screw up, people die around you.
一英里远距狙杀
伊拉克  Lutayfiyah  2004年4月9日
Lutayfiyah, Iraq--April 9, 2004.
伊拉克
路特菲亚
东经44.368北纬32.989
F连14名陆战队员在通往路特菲亚的路上巡查
14 Fox Company Marines patrol the roadway into Lutayfiyah.
他们的任务是搜寻路边炸弹及叛军
Their mission: Look for roadside bombs and insurgents.
美军巡逻队
一名海军陆战队狙击手和他的观察手
A Marine and his spotter overwatch
在1,000码外的的一个油罐顶上执行掩护
the patrol from atop an oil tank 1,000 yards away.
我在其中一个油罐顶上设好了观察点
I had set up a little observation post atop one of the towers,
这样我们就能俯看市区的风吹草动
so we could look down into the city, see what's going on,
看是否有人走动  查找可疑情况
see if anybody's moving around, just look for suspicious activity.
我带了支.50口径的反器材步枪
Toted the .50-cal up there with me.
说不准就会派上用场
You just never know when you might need it.
狙击手史蒂夫・瑞切特
一英里远距狙杀
狙击手史蒂夫・瑞切特 一英里远距狙杀
The sniper Steve Reichert one mile kill shot
瑞切特使用的是巴雷特M82-A3
Reichert's weapon: the Barrett M82-A3
特殊用途狙击步枪  .50口径的大家伙
Special Application Scoped Rifle, a .50-caliber beast.
那是一支.50口径巴雷特M82-A3半自动重狙
The weapon was a .50-caliber semiautomatic Barrett M82-A3.
武器型号:M82-A3特殊用途狙击步枪
口径: 12.7X99mm
枪口初速: 每秒2800英尺
最大有效射程: 2000码
弹匣容量10发  .50枪弹
It holds about ten rounds of .50-caliber ammunition.
配备广角瞄准镜
It has a barrel periscope.
最大有效射程2,000码
Max effective range, I'd say, is 2,000 yards.
用这种枪和枪弹  车辆都能打残
With that weapon and that round, you could stop a car or a truck.
瑞切特选用了这支.50口径的重狙
Reichert chooses the .50-cal
而非他通常使用的M40A3
over his standard M40A3.
如果我们遇到强风或其它情况
If we had strong winds or anything else,
我需要使用抗风能力好一点的
I wanted something that would actually buck the wind a little bit better,
另外  如果叛军躲在掩体后
and if the insurgents actually took up cover positions,
不管是在建筑物内或车辆后面
whether inside a building or behind a car,
我需要它能穿透掩体
I wanted something that could actually punch through the material
消灭敌人
and take them out.
眼前一切都很平静
All is quiet on the ground below
这时瑞切特的观察手看到路上有个东西
until Reichert's spotter picks up an object on the road.
塔克下士在路上看到一具动物尸体
Corporal Tucker noticed an animal in the road
前一天晚上还没有
that wasn't there the night before.
我用瞄准镜拉进看
I got on the scope and zoomed into it,
结果看到了一丝反光
and we saw just a little bit of glint coming off
估计是一截金属线
what we thought was a wire.
之前有人跟我们说过
They had mentioned to us in the past--
最近有叛军将路边炸弹安在动物尸体里
the insurgents are starting to emplace IEDs into dead animals,
然后扔在路旁
tossing them on the side of the road.
瑞切特用步话机通知了下面的陆战队员
Reichert radios the Marines on the ground.
距前方拐弯20码处可能有路边炸弹
We've got a potential IED in 20 yards around the bend.
-有路边炸弹  -收到
- IED!  - Roger that.
展开警戒
We're setting up a perimeter.
他们立刻在炸弹四周形成警戒圈
They cordon off the area surrounding the IED.
各就各位
Get it set!
封锁这里  快  封锁这里
Cordon it off, let's go, cordon it off!
在发现金属线反光的那一刻
When we actually saw the glint coming off the wires,
我们感觉好极了  总算不负使命
we felt good, like, "Hey, we've done our job."
他们会处理那个路边炸弹的
They would actually get the IED taken care of,
拆除它就不会有人被炸了
disarm it, nobody gets hurt.
我们在后面已就位
We're set up at the back side!
罗伯茨上士  你那边怎样
Staff Sarge Roberts, how you doing?
一切正常
All clear!
路边炸弹安全
IED is secure.
我们看着他们在炸弹周围展开警戒
We just watched them set up that perimeter around the IED,
然而30秒之后  一切突然爆发
then 30 seconds later, everything erupted.
先是一枚火箭弹袭击
We got hit with a RPG first,
紧接着AK步枪就向我们开火了
and then the AKs started coming.
在这么远的距离  我能看到事情的全过程
Being that far away, I could actually see things unfolding--
看到叛军是从哪里冒出来发射火箭筒的
where the insurgents appeared from and launched the RPGs,
然后就看见机枪打得到处尘土飞扬
and then you just saw dirt and dust kicking up everywhere
陆战队员们正遭受袭击
from machine gun fire the Marines were taking.
我一看到开始交火
Once I saw the firefight start to erupt,
就迅速估算了一下距离
I made a quick range estimation,
调整了瞄具参数
put the correct dope on the scope,
然后开始搜索狙击目标
and then just started scanning for targets of opportunity.
叛军在1,350码之外
The insurgents are 1,350 yards away,
也就是超过3/4英里的距离
a distance of more than three-quarters of a mile.
瑞切特调整了弹着点  将瞄具调至10+2
Reichert adjusts his range--or "Dopes the scope"-- to 10+2:
即1,000码射距  偏2角分
1,000 yards plus two minutes of angle.
下面的海陆队员一路打进城里
The Marines on the ground fight their way into the town
并以一处废弃的校舍作掩护
and take cover in an abandoned schoolhouse.
快  火力压制
Come on, come on! Suppressing fire!
敌人的数量远远超过他们
They are greatly outnumbered.
城里的其他叛军听到了交火声
All the other insurgents in the city heard gunfire.
大概都想去凑凑热闹
We were like, "Yeah, it's party time,"
于是抄起他们的AK步枪  加入战斗
So they grabbed their little AKs and went to the gunfire.
我们看见一两个家伙在屋顶上出现
We noticed one or two guys pop up on top of the roof,
我们要开始干活了
and that's when we went to work.
第一个家伙在屋顶上露了头
The first guy, I saw him pop up from the roof,
我将瞄准镜转向他  打开保险
swung the crosshairs over to him, flipped the weapon on kill,
将子弹射出
shot the round downrange.
塔克下士立即告诉我  打得太低了
Corporal Tucker immediately advised me, "Hey, you're way low,"
我立刻想到  显然他们已改变了方位
And then it clicked on my head: they've obviously changed positions.
我迅速再次调整了瞄准镜
Made another quick dope change on the scope,
又打出一发子弹
sent the next round downrange.
这次命中目标
That hit its mark.
只见一片血光飞溅
It was just a pink mist.
即便是在3/4英里之外
Even at three quarters of a mile,
.50枪弹也极具杀伤力
the .50-cal is devastating.
这种武器其实主要是
This actually was mainly designed for
为装甲运兵车这样的硬目标设计的
armor personnel carrier vehicles-- hard targets--
如果用它来打一个软目标  如人体
so when you hit a soft target --a person--
一下就打烂了
they just rip apart.
当那把大枪发射的时候  我心想
When that rifle went off, I thought,
埃德加・索铎
前海军陆战队员
我靠  后面是什么玩意
"Oh, man, what the hell is that behind me?"
我那时不知道他正在奋力歼敌
I didn't know he was actively engaging targets at the time.
陆战队员们被敌人的猛烈火力压制住了
The Marines are pinned down, taking heavy fire.
我们看到三个叛军从后面爬上一个楼梯井
We noticed three insurgents climbing up the back of a stairwell.
其中一人好像带着一挺RPK
Looked like one of them had an RPK,
目标
一种弹药带供弹的轻机枪  他背在背上
a belt-fed machine gun, slung over his back.
他们猫在一堵墙后
They ducked down behind a wall.
我立即瞄准他们可能藏身的位置
We immediately put the crosshairs on where I thought they were.
如果叛军将他们的机枪架好
If the insurgents get their machine gun set up,
地面上的海军陆战队员就麻烦了
the Marines on the ground are in trouble.
这几个叛军在1,600米开外
The insurgents are more than 1,600 meters away,
整整一英里的距离
a distance of one mile.
让情况更加复杂的是
Complicating the shot further,
瑞切特必须穿透一堵砖墙击中他们
Reichert must fire through a brick wall to hit them.
他有完美的高能弹药来做到这一点
He has the perfect ammo for the job:
劳福斯MK211
穿甲燃烧弹
.50口径的劳福斯MK211穿甲燃烧弹
the Raufoss, Mark 211 .50-caliber round.
当劳福斯穿甲弹击中墙体
When the Raufoss round impacts a concrete wall,
它会在墙一侧击出一个.50英寸的小洞
it punches a small .50-caliber hole on one side.
然后黑索金炸药被引爆
Then the RDX explodes.
推动钨合金穿甲弹头穿透墙体
You have the tungsten steel penetrator punching through,
而后锆燃烧剂在墙另一侧爆燃
zirconium sparks on the other side.
爆炸和弹片效果有如霰弹枪一般
You basically have a shotgun blast and shrapnel
还有个穿墙而过的弹头
and a penetrating dart flying through.
发射前瑞切特的观察手又作了最后调校
Reichert's spotter gives him last-minute adjustments for the shot.
这非常关键
It's really crucial to ensure
我们之间的沟通必须准确无误
the communication flowing back and forth are accurate
并对瞄准镜作出相应调整
and you're actually making the changes to the scope.
战术呼吸让瑞切特的瞄准稳定下来
Tactical breathing steadies Reichert's aim.
他开枪了
He fires.
这一枪准确击中了我们所希望的位置
The round landed exactly where we wanted it to.
劳福斯穿甲弹以超过2,500英尺每秒的速度
The Raufoss round blasts through the concrete wall
炸穿了坚固的墙体
at a speed in excess of 2,500 feet per second.
爆炸轰碎了叛军
The explosion obliterates the insurgents.
楼梯井对面的墙壁被染成一片血红
The wall on the opposite side of that stairwell just turned red.
再也没有看到他们三个爬起来
We didn't see the... the three of them get up.
其后12小时  瑞切特一直用这支.50大狙射击
Reichert stays on the .50 for the next 12 hours.
他的精准射击阻滞了叛军的进攻
His sharpshooting halts the insurgents' attack
挽救了地面海军陆战队员的生命
and saves Marines on the ground.
鉴于其英勇行为  他被授予铜星勋章
For his heroic actions, he receives the Bronze Star for Valor.
T1G训练场
2009年
T1G训练场  2009年
T1G Training Facilities, 2009.
五年后  史蒂夫・瑞切特又拿起了M82A3
Five years later, Steve Reichert is back behind the M82-A3,
他曾用来在一英里距离上消灭叛乱份子的利器
the weapon he used to take out insurgents from a mile away.
这玩意就像在你脸前四尺爆炸的迷你炮
It's a mini-explosion going off about four feet in front of your face.
冲击波很大  噪音很高
A large overpressure, a lot of noise.
成天打这也不是件舒服的事情
It's not a pleasant gun to shoot all day long.
打够三四十发  就不想再打了
30 or 40 rounds, and you want to quit.
不过还是很好的武器系统
Still a great weapon system.
2004年的四月
In April 2004,
我的武器系统  M82A3
my weapon system, the M82A3 was
插着塞满了Mk211拉弗斯弹的弹匣
loaded with magzines full of Mk211 Rafuss round and
这个子弹最终就是给坏人们品尝的
the business end of this round were the bad guys are experiencing
同一杆枪  同一种弹  同一个人
Same weapon, same round, same sniper.
瑞切特将使用12.7MM的拉弗斯弹药
Reichert will fire the .50-caliber Raufoss rounds
军方编号MK211的.50BMG高爆穿甲弹药
原是挪威NAMMO公司的拉弗斯AS  故得此名
打穿九英寸厚的水泥砖墙
into a nine-inch-thick cinderblock wall,
跟那次一英里绝杀上
the same type of wall insurgents hid behind
叛乱分子藏身的掩体是一样的
when he made his one-mile kill shot.
一旦弹头命中目标
Once this round impacts the target,
其内部的黑索金就会被引爆  造成一次小爆炸
the RDX will detonate, kind of create a mini-shape charge,
环三亚甲基三硝胺  缩写RDX  优异高爆炸药
所以如有任何易燃液体  汽油或别的什么
so if there are any flammable liquids-- gas, anything of that nature--
立马就会开始着火燃烧或是爆炸
it immediately detonates or catches fire.
开始喽
Going hot.
671格令重的弹头以每秒2850尺的速度击中墙
The 671-grain round hits the wall at 2,850 feet per second.
弹尖的引燃物
An incendiary mix in the nose of the bullet
会引爆弹头内部的爆炸物
ignites explosives in its core,
推动钨钢弹芯  穿透水泥
launching a tungsten steel penetrator through the concrete.
这是一块坚实的水泥墙
So, what we have here is a solid filled concrete wall.
看看一次爆炸产生的效应
You can see where the initial blast and explosion took effect.
还能清楚看到这个位置穿甲弹芯
You can actually see where the steel penetrator worked
是如何贯穿这块九英寸的水泥
all the way through a good nine inches of solid concrete
然后继续飞的
and popped out the other end.
为了模拟躲在墙壁后面的叛乱分子
To simulate the insurgents hiding behind the wall,
瑞切特放置了一块终端弹道测试用的凝胶
Reichert adds a block of ballistic gelatin,
密度和人体组织一样
the same consistency as human tissue.
那边四月  我看见三个叛乱分子
Back in April, I saw three insurgents
跑上了一幢房子的后楼梯
coming up the back stairs of a building.
我估计了下他们的可能所在
I picked where I thought they would be,
然后一发打穿墙
sent a round crashing into the wall.
弹头引爆 造成了霰弹效果一样的内侧崩漏杀伤
The round detonated, and you had that shotgun blast
直对着叛乱分子
coming into where the insurgents were.
凝胶的作用是演示
The gel will give you a good sense of,
如果有人处在这个区域
if there were a person sitting here,
子弹穿透后会把他怎么样
what would happen to him after this round penetrates.
双重听力保护
Double hearing protection.
这个武器的冲击波很大  所以一定要保护
The overpressure on this weapon system is quite significant, so, uh...
我一边的耳朵已被个路边炸弹震聋了
I'm already deaf in one ear from an IED;
所以不能再聋了
don't need the other ear gone.
开火
Firing.
拉弗斯弹头横贯水泥墙直接进了凝胶
The Raufoss round blasts to the wall and into the ballistic gelatin.
有好东西看了
This should be interesting.
以前还真没做过这样正儿八经的实验
Never done an actual test like this before.
也没看过慢动作
Never actually seen it in slow motion.
显而易见  MK211弹轻松穿过了第一层
Obviously, the Mark 211 round penetrated that first block, no problem.
爆炸在接触外墙层时发生
The explosion started to happen on the first panel of the block,
完全炸开了内墙层  而凝胶块
blew out the second panel of the blk, and then the gelatin block itself,
则吸收了大部分的碎片
caught the majority of the fragmentation.
杀伤空腔很大
The wound cavity is massive.
然后是被甲的大部分
And then, the majority of the jacket--
至于钨钢穿甲芯
the actual tungsten steel penetrator--
则毫无疑问地穿了出去
actually penetrated out the back end-- no surprise there--
打穿了这里这块水泥砖  继续飞
and then punched through this concrete block, and then continued on.
如果这里后面是个人
If there were a person back here,
会变成一个碎成很多块的人
they would be in many pieces right now.
弹道专家费尔南多・奎罗分析了损伤
Ballistics Expert Fernando Coelho analyzes the damage.
刀刃进去三英寸左右
Blade is going about three inches now,
就已经到空腔了
and it's already in the cavity.
奎罗已与不同政府机构合作20年
Coelho worked with numerous government agencies for 20 years.
水泥碎屑
There is actual cement material throughout the...
遍布了整个伤道
the wound path.
费尔南多・奎罗
EOTAC战术服装公司/弹道学家
很严重
This is just devastating.
如果是三个人排排坐
'Cause you could have had three people back-to-back,
这一发就是串个糖葫芦
and this round would have most likely gone through all three.
一英里  一堵墙  三个叛乱分子
One mile, one brick wall, three insurgents
搞定
gone.
我知道下面平地上有14个弟兄
I just knew I had 14 guys on the deck down there,
他们正受到袭击
and they were receiving fire.
距离不算优势  直到那晚才算
The distance didn't really click till, you know, that night.
此时此地  此枪此弹
Even at that distance, with that round,
唯有做到弹无虚发
as long as your rounds find their marks,
你才能在战场上扭转乾坤
you can definitely change the dynamics on the battlefield.
此长  彼消
Good for us, bad for them.
阿富汗的崇山峻岭间
High in the mountains of Afghanistan,
一位加拿大狙击手会超越瑞切特的一英里击杀
a Canadian sniper will eclipse Reichert's one-mile kill shot,
在一英里半距离上干掉一名塔利班分子
taking out a Taliban fighter one and a half miles away.
不知道他们是不是以为自己能侥幸逃生
I don't know if they just thought that today was their lucky day, but
但完全不是
it wasn't.
最远的一击
麦克米兰战术50长程狙击步枪
The McMillan Tac-50 Long Range Sniper Rifle.
.50弹的枪口初速在2700fps左右
A .50-caliber round leaves the muzzle at 2,700 feet per second.
威力与精度的结晶
A combination of power and accuracy,
战术50能在20个橄榄球场距离废掉一辆车
the Tac-50 is capable of taking out a vehicle 20 football fields away.
我头一次打战术50的时候实在吃惊不小
The very first time I fired the Tac-50 was an awakening
才知道原来世间有这么强力的武器
to know that there's something out there with that much power.
该怎么形容好呢
How would I describe it?
就是敌人的梦魇吧
Probably an enemy's worst nightmare.
狙击手  罗伯・弗隆
The sniper: Rob Furlong.
狙击手
罗伯・弗隆
史上最远狙杀
一英里半
史上最远狙杀  一英里半
Longest kill shot in history.One and a half miles.
此记录已在被英国羽林骑马兵下士柯栾格・哈里森打破
2009年11月  用L115A3射杀距离2475M  首发命中
阿富汗
2002年三月
March, 2002.
夏伊科峡谷
纬度:33.446769  经度:68.198038
美军发动了森蚺/林蟒行动
U.S. Forces launch Operation Anaconda.
任务是歼灭夏伊科峡谷区域的
The mission: Destroy Al-qaeda and Taliban forces
基地组织和塔利班武装
in the Shah-I-Kot Valley.
这个区域崎岖难走
The terrain is rugged and unforgiving.
漫山遍野都是敌人
The mountains filled with enemy fighters.
弗隆是加拿大狙击队的一员
Furlong is part of a Canadian sniper team
跟随美国特种部队行动
attached to U.S. Special Forces.
进到人家门口打仗总归是有点怕怕的
It's pretty humbling coming into somebody's home turf.
开进峡谷的那天  我差点吓坏了
Pushing into that valley that day, I'm almost in awe.
就像跑进了个鱼缸  看得见那些塔利班战士
Moving into a fishbowl and we could see all these Taliban fighters,
平均海拔  9000英尺
他们就在高地上
they're up on the higher ground.
对于这个海拔高度的作业  我完全没有经验
I had no experience in operating in those kind of altitudes
弗隆的武器  麦克米兰战术50
Furlong's weapon: The McMillan Tac-50.
武器型号:麦克米兰战术50
口径: 12.7X99mm
枪口初速: 每秒2700英尺
最大有效射程: 2190码
一款最大有效射程2190码的狙击步枪
A sniper rifle with a max effective range of 2,190 yards.
最初的目标是在1500米距离上的
The very first target we engaged was 1,500 meters.
这是森蚺行动中我们挑的
That was the closest target we would engage
距离最近的一个
during Operation Anaconda.
希望尽可能接近目标
We want to be close enough to the target
以尽量保证一枪毙命
that we can guarantee one shot, one kill.
只是在1500米距离上打人体靶
When you're shooting at a human-sized target at 1,500 meters,
变数实在太多
there's so many variables to take into place.
弗隆所处有海拔一万英尺高
Furlong works at elevations as high as 10,000 feet.
高海拔对于远距离射击有很大影响
The extreme altitude has a dramatic effect on long-range shots.
海拔每上升一千码  情况就完全不同
Every thousand feet you go up, it's a whole new set of equations.
军士长  马克・斯宾塞
英国陆军[已退役]
因为空气越来越稀薄  故而
Because the air's getting thinner, so therefore,
海拔
5000尺
枪口初速会让子弹打得更远
your muzzle velocities are increasing your time of flight.
海拔
8500尺
低海拔反而没有那么远
It's actually shorter from the distance further down.
海拔
10000尺
风偏对于我们的击杀率有很大影响
Winds played a huge factor what our, uh, hit ratio.
一击必杀的例子不是很多
Not a lot of one-round hits.
原因在于我们有时候会面对  比如
Reason being is we're dealing with, at times,
有时会面对最少三次横风
I remember at least three crosswinds and you just,
那就只能等最佳时机
you wait for that perfect moment.
要是我说没风就没风  那就好办了
It's great if I can get the winds to die out.
实际上怎么可能会没风
But how many times does three crosswinds die out?
根本不可能
They don't.
我们效率是如此之高
We were so effective.
很快就切断了他们所有的补给线
We had shut down all resupply lines
那些想要补给的
and the guys who would try to use them
就只贴着地慢慢爬
would actually get down on their faces and crawl.
不到一周
Within a week,
弗隆就打光了加拿大产的弹药
furlong runs out of his Canadian-made ammo.
有人给了我们些美国产的弹药
We had somebody offer us, uh, American-made ammunition
我们开始用的时候发现 这种子弹更热
and when we started using it we noticed that it was a hotter round.
美国产0.50（英寸）口径子弹
加拿大产0.50（英寸）口径子弹
我们用这个子弹能够打得更远
We were getting a lot longer distances out of this round.
至于是不是因为弹头更轻
Whether that round was a lighter round,
还是发射药燃烧得更快  我不清楚
whether it was a faster burning propellant, I don't know.
每一枪都是全新的一枪
Every shot that we made was new for us.
美国产0.50（英寸）口径子弹
加拿大产0.50（英寸）口径子弹
不管是因美国弹药更符合空气动力学
Whether the U.S. rounds are more aerodynamic
还是只是烧药更加速燃
or simply have a faster burning propellant,
结果都很惊人
the results are dramatic.
弗隆及其团队在超过一英里距离上都能命中
Furlong and his team take out enemy targets more than a mile away.
但他创纪录的那一枪尚未到来
But his longest shot is yet to come.
夏伊科谷地
The Shah-I-Kot Valley.
平均海拔  9000英尺
Mean altitude: 9,000 Feet.
射杀背景
夏伊科谷地
平均海拔  9000英尺
我们观察到有人步行穿越河谷
When somebody's walking on a river valley floor,
我当时在海拔8500尺处
I'm up at 8,500 feet.
正往下看
I'm looking down.
简直像是站在云端俯视众生
It's almost like being on the clouds looking at someone.
我们观察到了一个塔利班的三人队
We had observed a three-man Taliban team and
其中一个扛着RPK  7.62mm口径机枪
one of them had an RPK, which is a 7.62 machine gun on his shoulder,
目标
RPK是基于AKM设计衍生的一种班组轻机枪
我们决定解决那个
and it was decided that we would engage the Taliban fighter
扛RPK的塔利班份子
with the RPK on his shoulder.
我的搭档观测了目标  报给了我距离
My partner liaises the target, gives me the distance.
然后报给我风向变化
He starts to give me varying wind direction.
按密位制校准好我的瞄准镜
Its everything on milsm to enter in data into my scope
或者说是这种情况下  我得怎么打
or, in this case, what I'm gonna do to
才够得着这个距离
be able to reach that range
这可是一英里半的距离
You're talking about a mile and a half's distance
而他们在找对面山上的一个人型靶
and they're looking for a man-sized target on the side of a mountain.
实际上  这很不简单
Now, that in itself is quite a feat,
首先要定位那个人就不容易
to actually find that guy in the first place.
弗隆在想尽办法增加他的射程
Furlong looks for any way to get more distance on his shot.
他用回了一个老招
He resorts to an old sniper trick.
那天很暖和
It was a very warm day.
我就把弹药都铺开放在太阳底下晒
We had our ammo laid out in the sun--
一切为了射程
anything to increase range.
不会有很大的改观
It's not gonna make a huge difference,
但会对发射药的燃速有些许帮助
but it'll make a little difference for how propellant acts.
更快燃烧意味着能飞得更远
A faster burn allowing the round to travel slightly further.
鉴于角度和距离的局限
Because of the extreme angle and the distance,
弗隆用了伏击方式
Furlong uses the ambush method--
距离目标：2430米
海拔：8500英尺
在目标的行进路线上等候
leading the target or allowing it to walk into the path of the bullet.
我旋钮都转到最大
I max out my elevation drum.
最终射击位置
1.5英里外
风偏是最大值  等于我割除了瞄准镜半边
My windage is maxed out, so I'm halfing out my scope,
我的意思是说  我在用密位点给提前量
and what I mean by that is, I'm leading with my mil-dots,
但同时我也在用密位补偿仰角
but I'm also using my mil-dots for elevation, as well.
类似对割我的瞄准镜
So, I'm kind of halfing my scope
来找这个瞄准点
to where I believe my point of aim is.
比方说一个瞄准镜
When you have a scope, uh,
通常人都会对着这个点瞄准
usually this is what everybody's thinking about for a point of aim.
但如果我在留提前量
If I'm leading a target, uh,
目标从右往左走
and I have a target walking from right to left,
他在动  我却不动  在这个点等他
he's walking and I'm waiting for him to hit this point right here.
一旦目标到了这个密位点
Once that target is at my point of aim,
就是开枪时刻
that's when the shot's released.
标准伏击
That's an ambush.
不是准心压着目标开火
Not releasing on the crosshairs.
这个情况下  是一个密位的提前量
You release this is what you're using
作为瞄准点  再开火
for a point of aim and that's one mil.
大体上一个四密位的提前量
Basically with a four mil lead,
和四密位的高度调整
and a four mil for elevation,
瞄准点大概就在这里
your point of aim roughly would be in this area.
弗隆瞄高了四个密位  实际大约15尺
Furlong aims 4 mils, or roughly 15 feet above,
瞄左四个密位  大约也是15尺
and approximately 4 mils or 15 feet to the left of his target.
这些提前量能补偿弹头下降  风偏和偏转造成的误差
These holds compensate for bullet drop, wind and spin drift.
弗隆保持稳定  瞄准
furlong steadys himself, takes aim
瞄准  开火
takes aim, and fires
我的搭档告诉我  没打中
And from my partner, it's miss.
三发未中
Off three.
右边有四
Right four.
不管是什么样的理由  跟塔利班交锋时候
For whatever reason, when dealing with the Taliban,
他们总是不怕死一样
they didn't show a lot of fear.
有时候对着他们开上好几枪
You would shoot at them sometimes and,
他们动都不动
uh, they wouldn't even move.
他们也知道自己在被人打
And they knew they were being shot at.
子弹会在脚边溅起尘土或命中他们身边物件
Like the splash would hit by their feet or an object next to them.
我不知道他们是不是以为
I don't know if they just thought that
自己能侥幸逃生
today was their lucky day but,
但完全不是
it wasn't.
弗隆的观察手跟踪第一发子弹的
Furlong's spotter follows the vapor trail
子弹漩涡
尾迹
尾迹或叫子弹漩涡
or swirl of the bullet on his first shot,
然后观察到当击中地面后弹头造成的
then observes the splash or dirt kicked up by the round
尘土四溅
as it hits the ground.
为了量化  你可以想象
To quantify that, if you could imagine
观察手看到点50子弹
the observer watched a .50-caliber bullet
如何飞过一英里半扎进泥里
at a mile and a half away impact the ground,
然后根据弹着点通知我如何修正
and then he called adjustments from where the bullet landed
才能在下一发确保打中敌人
to where he knew the bullet had to be to hit the enemy.
弗隆准备他的第二发
Furlong sets up for his second shot.
他们分了三路
They go three different directions--
相隔都不远  离散开的地方约20至30英尺
not too far-- roughly 20 to 30 feet, to where they scatter.
但我能看到他
but I can see him
弗隆打了第二发
Furlong fires his second shot.
打偏了  命中了一个塔利班士兵的背包
He misses, hitting the Taliban soldier's backpack.
刚好是在第二个和第三个人中间
Well, between the second and third,
没有修正必要
there was no correction needed.
我知道接下来会发生什么
I knew exactly what had to happen
可我还是要打出这第三发
and I wanted to get that third shot downrange.
弗隆和他目标之间隔了一英里半
One and a half miles separate Furlong and his target.
开火
He fires.
弗隆的子弹以2700fps的速度离膛
Furlong's round leaves the rifle at 2,700 feet per second.
外弹道
飞行时间  四秒
Time of flight: Four seconds.
终结目标
Target eliminated.
我知道他倒下了  不过也就这样了
I know he went down but that's about it.
如果点50打到你
If a .50-cal round hit you,
就都不用想以后的事了
you're not gonna live to tell about it.
此弹必杀
It's a devastating round.
这是一颗能打穿你身体
You're talking about a projectile going through you
留下个比拇指还大的洞那样的弹头
that's roughly a little bit larger than your thumb.
罗伯・弗隆一英里半的射杀
Rob Furlong's mile and a half kill shot
卡洛斯・哈斯库克是用加了瞄准镜的M2重机枪打的
距离2500码  本片此前并未提及
超越卡洛斯・哈斯库克之前的记录157码
shatters Carlos Hathcock's previous record by 157 yards
我知道卡洛斯・哈斯库克是谁
I knew who Carlos Hathcock was,
但我不知道那次是多少距离
but didn't know what the distance was.
不知道是不是对我冲击很大
I don't know if it really has hit me.
我只是当它是我的本职工作
I always just took it as, uh, I was just doing my job.
指该片制作时间  此记录已被打破
罗伯・弗隆的记录至今仍是第一
Rob Furlong's record still stands today,
而在亚利桑那的高山之间
but high in the mountains of Arizona,
一位前海豹队员在尝试再现弗隆的一英里半狙杀
an ex-Navy Seal tries to duplicate his shot from a mile and a half away.
弹道是一门科学  是针对不同的武器
Ballistics is a science... of the certain weapon,
不同的口径  不同子弹的
and the certain caliber, the certain bullet.
怎样用一枚做成流线型的金属块
How you can take a small piece of steel that's formed in a cone
从一个金属管子里以极高速度飞出去
and shoot it down another tube of steel at a high rate of speed
然后准确地不断命中红心
and then be accurate enough to repeat that over and over and over again.
在狙击手扣下扳机打出那一发子弹前
Before that sniper pulls the trigger and delivers that shot
他必须要看透大自然
he must outguess Mother Nature.
外弹道
外弹道是子弹抗争于大自然的艺术
External ballistics is the art of that bullet handling Mother Nature.
一般而言  海拔越高  弹速越快
You might see a faster bullet at different elevations.
海拔
5000尺
8500尺
再加上摩擦力重力还有别的要素参与
With drag and gravity and other things that come into play
海拔
10000尺
会让子弹落点不同
will help the bullet hit differently.
子弹本身的飞行轨迹  明确飞行时间
The bullet's flight path itself, understanding time of flight,
明确子弹  步枪分别的温度
understanding heat on both
还有大气温度和横风
the bullet, the rifle, the wind--
都是狙击手必须调整的
snipers must be attuned to that.
夏伊科峡谷
阿富汗  2002年
森蚺行动  2002年3月
Operation Anaconda. March, 2002.
狙击手们会遇到的最为极端的弹道环境之一
One of the most extreme ballistic environments a sniper will ever face.
加拿大狙击手罗伯・弗隆对抗着高原反应
Canadian sniper Rob Furlong battles dizzying altitudes,
变幻不定的横风  和那险恶的山岭
shifting crosswinds and treacherous mountains.
他从一英里半距离干掉了一名塔利班机枪手
He takes out a Taliban machine gunner from a mile and a half away.
史上最长距离狙杀
The longest kill shot in history.
我曾开玩笑说
I've joked about it, and maybe
如果我再花一个月去再现这次射击
if I spend the next month trying to replicate it--
罗伯特・弗隆下士
加拿大陆军[已退役]
我还不知道我能不能再做到
I don't know, could I do it again?
我倒是希望我能
I would like to think I can. I mean,
是不是那天天地星辰都眷顾我来着
were all the stars and moons aligned that day?
我是真不知道
I don't know
麦克米兰训练中心  北靶场
McMillan Training Facility-- North Range.
亚利桑那西北
Northwest Arizona.
赖安・麦克米兰  退役海豹队员  正尝试再现
Ryan McMillan, ex-Navy SEAL, will try to replicate
罗伯・弗隆的一英里半狙杀  用的也是同一种武器
Rob Furlong's mile-and-a-half kill shot using the same weapon:
麦克米兰战术50远距狙击步枪
a McMillan Tac-50 Long Range Sniper Rifle.
这样的射击是人所能想到的最困难的一种
This shot is really one of the most difficult shots you can ever imagine.
不仅仅是那2430米的距离
Not only the distance at 2,430 meters,
还有横风  环境因素
but also the wind, the environmental factors,
所有都参杂进来使这种射击难度极高
everything that goes into it that makes it a very difficult shot.
赖安・麦克米兰
麦克米兰国际集团的副总裁  前海豹队员
马克・斯宾塞  前英国陆军狙击手
Mark Spicer, former British Army Sniper and
麦克米兰国际集团训练部的主管
Director of Training for McMillan Group International,
开车出去准备射击的标靶
drives out to set up the target for the shot.
所能看见的  是我们已经走了
You can see now, because we've been going
军士长  马克・斯宾塞
英国陆军[已退役]
这么远的路了  终于距离一样了
such a distance already, just how far away this target is.
我们用的是白色的人形靶纸
What we've got is a white paper human representative target
画着恐怖分子拿的典型AK特征步枪
of a terrorist armed with the sort archetypical AK-47
代表广泛存在的恐怖主义
associated with terrorism in general.
在上面插了面提高能见度的红旗
What we attached was the high visibility flag to the top of the mass.
旗子的作用是给出恐怖分子靶所在处的
Now, what that flag will do is that will give me an indication of
风向的具体情况
exactly what the wind is doin the target end.
目标在2400米距离上了
Okay, this target itself is at 2,400 meters.
如果你现在抬头看看周围山顶
If you now look around up to the top of the hillside
能看见一辆白车停在山脊上
you can see the white vehicle that's on the ridgeline.
那就是我们的开火位置
That's going to be what the  firing point is.
往那方向看  能看见一条干的河床
If you look straight out here you can see a wash
一直通到山脚下
that runs up into the base of the mountains here.
顺着河床再在往上看
If you follow that wash all the way up,
右边有个树丛
there's a patch of trees on the right.
树丛再左边一点就是我们的目标了
Just to the left of that patch of trees is our target.
这样你就能体会那具体有多远了
As you can see how far away that is and
这么一枪会有多难
how difficult of a shot that must've been to make.
海拔  1997英尺
山区地形类似阿富汗
The mountainous terrain is similar to Afghanistan,
但是海拔却低了接近7000尺
but the elevation is almost 7,000 feet lower.
更大空气密度意味赖安的子弹会飞得更慢更近
heavier air means Ryan's hot won't carry as fast or as far
我命中概率看来非常小
My chances of making this shot are pretty slim.
但不管怎样我们都要试它一试
But we're going to give it a shot anyway.
我先上来射击用的是  M33普通弹
I'm going to first shoot with this, uh, ball M33 ammo.
我现在要做的是子弹上靶
What I'm going to do here is just get on target with this.
你要我先打上河床看看么  马克
You want me to at the wash first, Mark?
这样我们能看见点尘土
So we can see some splash?
就往目标右边一点
Just to the right of the target.
赖安瞄准了目标右边一点的沙地
Ryan aims at a sandy spot near the target.
命中沙土能给观察手提供可见的弹着
Hitting the sand creates a visible "Splash" for his spotter.
马克就能在此弹着的基础上给出修正
Mark can then give him corrections based on that impact
并帮助他命中一英里半上的目标
and get him onto the target a mile-and-a-half downrange.
观察手就位
Spotter on.
射手待发
Shooter ready.
开火
Send it.
没有
赖安的子弹命中了目标周围的植被区
Ryan's shot impacts somewhere in the vegetation surrounding the target.
没有可见弹着标识
There is no visible splash.
我觉得吧 我们往下移
靠左往河床那个方向
那就是目标的七点钟方向了
-是目标七点钟方向  -好
因为那样比较直接
不如说是我们进去的那条路
试试能否在那弄点动静出来
没有
目标周围茂密的植被
The dense vegetation around the target
使得观察弹着的痕迹非常困难
makes it difficult to detect any sign of the round's impact.
赖安对准了一堆土
Ryan takes aim at a patch of dirt.
观察手就位
射手待发
开火
还是没有
你打进那堆叶子里面去了
到底是高了还是低了
You have any idea if it's high or low?
完全不知道  什么都看不见
没有尾流或别的什么
这样就能对这种射击的难度有直观体会了
马克在找尾流  弹头后面的白色蒸汽轨迹
Mark is looking for "Swirl," The vapor trail of the bullet,
产生于弹头推开前方空气运动时
created as it displaces the air in its path.
观察手利用尾流来追踪子弹的飞行轨迹
Spotters use swirl to pick up the flight path of the bullet.
风变大了
The wind kicks up,
在靶场上达到15到20英里每小时
blowing gusts of 15 to 20 miles per hour across the range.
环境使他们最终不可能
Conditions make it virtually impossible
捕捉到子弹的尾迹
to detect the bullet's vapor trail.
没有
完全没有
Not a thing.
我也什么都没看到
I didn't see a damn, thing either.
这天  赖安・麦克米兰
On this day, Ryan McMillan,
前海豹并专业射手  没法看透大自然
ex-Navy Seal and expert marksman, can't outguess Mother Nature.
这样的地形
With the terrain here, um,
非常接近阿富汗
it's very similar to what you would see in Afghanistan.
那里有不同向的风
They have different directions of wind.
当我看目标时
And as I look at the target--
目标上的旗子现在  是忽左忽右的
flags on the target right now, they're going from left to right.
实际上我们能看见的不同区域里
So every different place that we can actually see the wind
风向都是不一样的
is going in a different direction.
射手前面风向是从右到左
From right to left here at the-- at the, uh, shooter.
第一个弹着附近是从右到左
Also right to left at the first spot
到了峡谷又变成从左到右了
and left to right back in the valley.
不过对子弹影响最大的地方还是在枪口
And the place that affects your bullet the most is right at muzzle.
所以如果有风这样来
So if you have a wind going one way,
目标
比如说在枪口处从右往左
from let's say right to left at the muzzle,
会导致你的弹头一直往左偏
it's going to push your bullet longer down its path
并且一直影响
and it's going to affect it more.
目标
等该命中目标时  你就不知道它飞哪去了
And then by the time it gets to the target you just never know.
很难的一枪
It's a very difficult shot.
你要来试试吗
You want to take a shot at it?
不了
No.
从罗伯・弗隆的破纪录射击
From Rob Furlong's record-breaking shot
到伊森・普雷斯的费卢杰屋顶神射
to Ethan Place's sharpshooting on a Fallujah rooftop,
总有个地方  总有那么一颗弹头飞速掠过
somewhere, a lone bullet hurtles through space
与那全然不知的目标相遇
on a collision course with an unwitting target.
射击的另一端是一名狙击手
On the other end of that shot is a sniper,
具备大师级的弹道知识和神射技巧
posessing a mastery of bullistic, marksmanship
及最重要的  一枪毙命的觉悟
most importantly,the mindset of one shot, one kill
要明白你是个猎杀人的猎手
Understand that you are a hunter of man
这是你的职业  然后全神贯注于十字线
and this is what you do and then focus on the reticle.
就能帮你顺利过关
That'll get you through.
要找到有这样觉悟  这样纪律性的
It's hard to find somebody who has a mindset to
这样全心投入的人  非常之难
be that disciplined, be that dedicated to something.
而要找到能够让神准技术
And it's extreme to find that person,
上到全新境界的人  更是难上加难
who he define marksmanship to another level
狙击手是战场上最致命的武器
A sniper is the most deadly weapon on the battlefield.
因为他有耐心  有技术
'Cause he's got patience, he's got the skill set,
且能掩藏  融入环境  并骗过你的眼睛
and he can hide, blend and deceive.
你根本逃不过狙击手的猎杀
There's no place you can hide from a sniper.
一旦狙击手锁定目标  你必死无疑
If the sniper wants you, he's going to get you.